<top>
  <data> &lt;h1&gt;Digital Pali Reader - Help File&lt;/h1&gt;</data>
  <data> &lt;p&gt;If you are reading this, you have most likely got the Pali Reader up and</data>
  <data> running on your computer. If it is up but not running, maybe this document</data>
  <data> will help.&lt;/p&gt;</data>
  <data> &lt;h2&gt;&lt;b&gt;Notes:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;</data>
  <data> &lt;ul&gt;</data>
  <data> &lt;li&gt;The reader was created for my own personal use, but anyone is welcome to use</data>
  <data> or distribute what I have made for their own benefit or the benefit of others.</data>
  <data> &lt;br&gt;</data>
  <data> &lt;/li&gt;</data>
  <data> &lt;li&gt;Some of the words 'recognized' by the reader are still incorrectly so, and many more are not yet recognized.</data>
  <data> Please bear with me, I will try to correct this as I have time.&lt;/li&gt;</data>
  <data> &lt;/ul&gt;</data>
  <data> &lt;hr&gt;</data>
  <data> &lt;h2&gt;What is it?&lt;/h2&gt;</data>
  <data> &lt;p&gt;The Digital Pali Reader (DPR) is a tool, much like a hard-copy language reader, facilitating study of the Pali language at an</data>
  <data> advanced level. It contains the entire Myanmar version of the Pali tipitaka, as well as commentaries and sub-commentaries where available.  It also includes the Visuddhimagga, Abhidhammatthasangaha and several ancient grammatical texts composed in Pali, all available for analysis and translation.  Rather than offering a translation for the text being</data>
  <data> read, the DPR is like an ordinary text reader, which will normally include a dictionary with all of the difficult words</data>
  <data> found in the reader. The DPR differs from an ordinary reader in several</data>
  <data> respects:&lt;/p&gt;</data>
  <data> &lt;ol&gt;</data>
  <data> &lt;li&gt;The DPR allows for instant lookup of words, simply by clicking on a word</data>
  <data> in the passage being read. This avoids time spent looking for the word</data>
  <data> in a hard-copy dictionary or in another place on one's computer.&lt;/li&gt;</data>
  <data> &lt;li&gt;The DPR has a built in search function similar to that of the CSCD. Whereas the CSCD allows for only global searches or searches of entire pitakas, the DPR provides Nikaya and Book searches as well, as well as allowing advanced regular expression searches.&lt;/li&gt;</data>
  <data> &lt;li&gt;The dictionary files in the DPR were not designed specifically for the</data>
  <data> purpose at hand, and of course word-to-definition matches are sometimes incorrect</data>
  <data> due to imperfect</data>
  <data> analysis.&lt;/li&gt;</data>
  <data> &lt;li&gt;The DPR includes several dictionaries: Pali-English, English-Pali, Pali proper names, and Concise Pali Dictionary, as well as a searchable compilation of terms discussed in the commentaries and sub-commentaries. These can be directly accessed from the control panel under the "Dictionary" section. &lt;/li&gt;</data>
  <data> &lt;li&gt;The DPR has several useful auxiliary utilities, including:</data>
  <data> &lt;ul&gt;</data>
  <data> &lt;li&gt;bookmark and quote clipboard for keeping important passages&lt;/li&gt;</data>
  <data> &lt;li&gt;a Pali conversion utility that converts to and from Velthius and Unicode scripts&lt;/li&gt;</data>
  <data> &lt;li&gt;transliteration of Pali into Thai, Devanagari and Myanmar scripts &lt;/li&gt;</data>
  <data> &lt;li&gt;a Pali language quiz to test your vocabulary and a declension quiz to test your grammar&lt;/li&gt;</data>
  <data> &lt;li&gt; random English quotes from Buddhavacana, by S. Dhammika&lt;/li&gt;</data>
  
  <data> &lt;/ul&gt;</data>
  <data> &lt;/li&gt;</data>
  <data> &lt;/ol&gt;</data>
  <data> &lt;p&gt;While the DPR is far from perfect, it is sure to be useful for intermediate Pali students</data>
  <data> who wish to advance their studies to a higher level.&lt;br&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</data>
  <data> &lt;hr&gt;</data>
  <data> &lt;h2&gt;How to Use:&lt;/h2&gt;</data>
  <data> &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Note:&lt;/b&gt; If any problem arises in the functioning of the reader, just press F5 to reset the reader&lt;/p&gt;</data>
  <data> &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Note:&lt;/b&gt; Many common tasks are now mapped to keys, which may be used instead of the buttons themselves, as follows:&lt;br&gt;</data>
  <data> &lt;ul&gt;</data>
  <data> &lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;1,2,3&lt;/b&gt; for the three views (RAD)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;p,g,n&lt;/b&gt; for opening the previous, current (g) and next sections &lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;d,c,t&lt;/b&gt; for the three tools in the bottom frame &lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt; &lt;b&gt;x&lt;/b&gt; to open/close the control panel &lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt; &lt;b&gt;s&lt;/b&gt; to send selected text to the convertor, or the entire section if no text is selected.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt; &lt;b&gt;,&lt;/b&gt; and &lt;b&gt;.&lt;/b&gt; to go back and forth between dictionary entries (PED and DPPN).&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt; &lt;b&gt;%,!,#,*,?,@&lt;/b&gt; for each of the six buttons at the bottom (see below).&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</data>
  <data> &lt;p&gt;The right side of the screen contains the main controls. Basic use should require little explanation. What follows is a brief explanation of all of the controls in the control panel:&lt;/p&gt;</data>
  <data> &lt;ul&gt;</data>
  <data> &lt;li&gt;At the top, there is the list of nikayas, books and sub-sections for </data>
  <data> each book. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/li&gt;</data>
  <data> &lt;li&gt;Below that, there are four sets of buttons: &lt;table class="butc"&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="lbut" onmouseover="document.body.style.cursor='pointer'; this.style.backgroundImage='url(images/lb1.png)';" onmouseout="document.body.style.cursor='auto'; this.style.backgroundImage='url(images/lb0.png)';" title="Retrieve previous section (p)" &gt;&lt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class="sbut"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class="mbut" onmouseover="document.body.style.cursor='pointer'; this.style.backgroundImage='url(images/mb1.png)';" onmouseout="document.body.style.cursor='auto'; this.style.backgroundImage='url(images/mb0.png)';" title="Retrieve current section (g)" &gt;go&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class="sbut"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class="rbut" onmouseover="document.body.style.cursor='pointer'; this.style.backgroundImage='url(images/rb1.png)';" onmouseout="document.body.style.cursor='auto'; this.style.backgroundImage='url(images/rb0.png)';" title="Retrieve next section (n)" &gt;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt; </data>
  <data> These buttons load the actual text.  "Go" brings up the current section, and the others bring up the previous and next sections in the current book.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;</data>
  <data> &lt;table class="butc"&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style="background-image:url(images/lb1.png)"  id="dhierm" class="lbut"&gt;M&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class="sbut"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td id="dhiera" class="mbut" onmouseover="document.body.style.cursor='pointer'" onmouseout="document.body.style.cursor='auto'" title="Change to Aṭṭhakathā" &gt;A&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class="sbut"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td id="dhiert" class="rbut"  title="Change to Ṭīkā"  onmouseover="document.body.style.cursor='pointer'" onmouseout="document.body.style.cursor='auto'"&gt;T&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt; These buttons change the set of texts to be studied.  "M" switches to the root canonical text, "A" to the commentary, and "T" to the subcommentary.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;</data>
  <data>&lt;table class="butc"&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style="background-image:url(images/lb1.png)" id="cdifM" class="lbut" onmouseover="document.body.style.cursor='pointer'" onmouseout="document.body.style.cursor='auto'" title="Show Dictionary Frame (d)" &gt;D&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class="sbut"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td id="cofM" class="mbut" onmouseover="document.body.style.cursor='pointer'" onmouseout="document.body.style.cursor='auto'" title="Show Convertor Frame (c)" &gt;C&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class="sbut"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td id="scfM" class="rbut"  title="Show Textpad Frame (t)"  onmouseover="document.body.style.cursor='pointer'" onmouseout="document.body.style.cursor='auto'"&gt;T&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt; These buttons switch what is shown in the bottom left frame. "D" shows the dictionary frame, "C" shows the text converter, and "T" shows the text pad.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;</data>
  <data>&lt;table class="butc"&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td id="RM" class="lbut" onmouseover="document.body.style.cursor='pointer'" onmouseout="document.body.style.cursor='auto'" title="Maximize Read Frame (1)" &gt;R&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class="sbut"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td id="AM" class="mbut" onmouseover="document.body.style.cursor='pointer'" onmouseout="document.body.style.cursor='auto'" title="Restore Frames (2)" &gt;A&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class="sbut"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td id="DM" class="rbut"  title="Maximize Dictionary Frame (3)"  onmouseover="document.body.style.cursor='pointer'" onmouseout="document.body.style.cursor='auto'"&gt;D&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt; These buttons change the layout of the reader.  "R" shows only the section being read with the small panel at the bottom, "A" shows the standard analysis view, and "D" maximizes the dictionary frame.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;</data>
  <data> &lt;/li&gt;</data>
  <data> &lt;li&gt;Next below that, There is a section titled</data>
  <data> &quot;Bookmarks&quot;. &lt;br&gt;</data>
  <data> &lt;br&gt;</data>
  <data> The first row here contains a drop-down list of saved bookmarks and a button</data>
  <data> &lt;input type="button" class="btn" value="&gt;" title="Load this bookmark"&gt;. To open a saved bookmark, including the scrolled distance, select</data>
  <data>  a bookmark from the list and click on the &lt;input type="button" class="btn" value="&gt;" title="Load this bookmark"&gt; button.&lt;br&gt;</data>
  <data> &lt;br&gt;</data>
  <data> The second row contains a text field and a button &lt;input type="button" class="btn" value="S" title="Set Bookmark"&gt;. To create a</data>
  <data> bookmark for the current page and scrolled distance, type in a name for the</data>
  <data> bookmark and click on the button &lt;input type="button" class="btn" value="S" title="Set Bookmark"&gt;. As an option, if you first select some text, that text will be added to the bookmark in the bookmark list.&lt;br&gt;</data>
  <data> &lt;br&gt;</data>
  <data> Note: Clicking on the title "Bookmarks" opens up an advanced bookmark manager where you can view/add descriptions, change names, and delete bookmarks, as well as edit or clear the history.&lt;br&gt;</data>
  <data> &lt;br&gt;&lt;/li&gt;</data>
  <data> &lt;li&gt;Next below that, there is the search function and a manual dictionary</data>
  <data> lookup. &lt;br&gt;</data>
  <data> &lt;br&gt;</data>
  <data> To use the search function, first select a nikaya and book (optionally) at the top (changing the other fields doesn't affect the search), switch to mula or atthakatha, enter the string for which to search (or multiple strings seperated</data>
  <data> by the "+" sign) and then click on either &lt;input type="button" class="btn" value="T" title="Search through the entire mul or att filelist"&gt;, &lt;input type="button" class="btn" value="N" title="Search through the entire Nik&#x0101;ya"&gt;, or &lt;input type="button" class="btn" value="B" title="Search through the entire book"&gt; buttons under "Text Search".  </data>
  <data> &lt;input type="button" class="btn" value="T" title="Search through the entire mul or att filelist"&gt; searches the entire mula or atthakatha filelist, &lt;input type="button" class="btn" value="N" title="Search through the entire Nik&#x0101;ya"&gt; searches an entire Nikaya, and</data>
  <data> &lt;input type="button" class="btn" value="B" title="Search through the entire book"&gt; searches an entire book.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Note that javascript regular expressions may be used in the search (use with care!), for example: &lt;b&gt;,&lt;/b&gt; (comma) matches any character, &lt;b&gt;[^a]&lt;/b&gt; matches any character except "a", etc.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;  To search for a page number, use the following syntax: P1.0001, P1.0002, etc., where "P" (or V, M, T) is the PTS pagination set, the first "1" is the volume, and the following (must be four digits) is the page number.  After entering the page code, click "B" to search the current book, or "N" for the current nik&#x0101;ya.&lt;/li&gt;</data>
  <data> &lt;br&gt;</data>
  <data> &lt;li&gt;The manual dictionary lookup has six choices. "DPR" runs an analysis on the word or passage at hand as it normally would. This only works for full words and phrases.</data>
  <data> "ATT" (Atthakath&#257;) brings up a list of words or phrases explained in the commentaries.</data>
  <data> "PED" (Pali-English Dictionary), "EPD" (English-Pali), "DPN" (Dictionary of Pali Proper Names), and "CPD" (Concise Pali Dictionary) bring up entries in the selected dictionary</data>
  <data> beginning with the letter sequence as it is typed. If you choose "PED" and type "aa" into the box, for example, it will come up with a list of Pali-English Dictionary entries starting with a long "&#257;". The CPD allows multiple language translations from Pali, provided that the appropriate dictionary file has been installed (see instructions above).  All lookup functions except DPR allow inner-word search by prefixing the search term with "*".  Note that this disables the "as-you-type" results in order to avoid excessive CPU usage, and you must press the &lt;input type="button" class="btn" value=">" title="Edit or look up a word - start with '*' for inner-word matches (requires clicking the '>' button)"&gt; button to execute the search.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/li&gt;</data>
  <data> &lt;li&gt;</data>
  <data> The last set of buttons has some technical links:&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;input type="button" class="btn" value="%" title="Set configuration"&gt;&lt;input type="button" class="btn" value="!" title="Reset configuration"&gt; These buttons allow one to adjust the size and colors of the reader as well as other misc. options.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;</data>
  <data> &lt;input type="button" class="btn" value="#" title="Pali Quiz"&gt;&lt;input type="button" class="btn" value="*" title="Quote of the Moment"&gt; The "#" button opens a Pali quiz to test your vocabulary.  The "*" button displays a random quote from the book, Buddhavacana.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;</data>
  <data> &lt;input type="button" class="btn" value="?" title="Help (New Window)"&gt;&lt;input type="button" class="btn" value="@" title="Send Feedback"&gt; "?" shows this help file and "@" allows you to contact me via email.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/li&gt;</data>
  <data> &lt;li&gt;</data>
  <data>  The final section below that has a drop-down menu to choose which script to read the texts in.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/li&gt;</data>
  <data> &lt;/ul&gt;</data>
  <data> &lt;p&gt;Once you have retrieved a section, click on any</data>
  <data> word as you read through to bring up an analysis of the word and hopefully at least one (hopefully correct) definition from one of the three dictionaries.&lt;/p&gt;</data>
  <data> &lt;p&gt;Finally, there are some hidden tools in the DPR; hidden because I didn't kow where to put them.  Links to them will be placed here:&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;a href="etc/grammar/GMD/index.html" style="color:blue" target="_blank"&gt;A Practical Grammar of the Pali Language by Charles Duroiselle&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;a href="etc/grammar/cheet.html" style="color:blue" target="_blank"&gt;Pali Cheet Sheet by Alan McClure&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</data>
  <data> &lt;hr&gt;</data>
  <data> &lt;h2&gt;Gratitude:&lt;/h2&gt;</data>
  <data> &lt;p&gt;Thanks first and foremost to Alexander Genaud, without whom I would still be pulling my hair out (figuratively) waiting for the script to load a single section. Without his initial help there would be no DPR.</data>
  <data> Without his later advice we would still be accessing one paragraph at a time and</data>
  <data> the data would be pre-analyzed and thus difficult to read. There would also be</data>
  <data> no search function. Special thanks also to Alan McClure, Ven. Gavesako, Peter</data>
  <data> Masefield, Lin Qian, and Leland George for spotting errors in the script and offering encouragement and suggestions. Thanks to Upaasako, our first team member who helped with the bookmarking system among other things. Thanks to John Bullit for his link on &lt;a href="http://www.accesstoinsight.org/outsources/pali.html"&gt;www.accesstoinsight.org&lt;/a&gt; as well as for graciously hosting a PHP script providing the list of sutta translations used by the DPR. And thanks to everyone else who helped out in the project in any small or large way - sotthi vo hotu. Special impersonal credit is due to all of those people involved in creating and providing publicly-available electronic versions of the following resources:&lt;br&gt;</data>
  <data> &lt;ul&gt;</data>
  <data> &lt;li&gt;The Myanmar Pali Tipitaka&lt;/li&gt;</data>
  <data> &lt;li&gt;The Pali English Dictionary&lt;/li&gt;</data>
  <data> &lt;li&gt;Concise Pali English Dictionary&lt;/li&gt;</data>
  <data> &lt;li&gt;Concise English Pali Dictionary&lt;/li&gt;</data>
  <data> &lt;li&gt;Dictionary of Pali Proper Names&lt;/li&gt;</data>
  <data> &lt;li&gt;Buddha Vacana&lt;/li&gt;</data>
  <data> &lt;/ul&gt;</data>
  <data> &lt;p&gt;Should this software infringe upon anyone's felt right to forbid the copying of any of the above or other materials, I apologize for the felt violation. I am sorry to know that some people feel this way about generally useful things that benefit the public immensely when distributed freely. May all be happy and well.</data>
  <data> &lt;hr&gt;</data>
  <data> &lt;h2&gt;Final Words:&lt;/h2&gt;</data>
  <data> &lt;p&gt;1) Please write to me with errors, bugs, spiders, etc. My email is</data>
  <data>  &lt;a href="mailto:yuttadhammo@gmail.com"&gt;yuttadhammo@gmail.com&lt;/a&gt;.</data>
  <data> &lt;/p&gt;</data>
  <data> &lt;p&gt;2) Please check our </data>
  <data> &lt;a href="http://pali.sirimangalo.org/blog/"&gt;weblog&lt;/a&gt; for new updates.&lt;/p&gt;</data>
  <data> &lt;p&gt;Best wishes and good luck,&lt;/p&gt;</data>
  <data> &lt;p&gt;Yuttadhammo&lt;/p&gt;</data>
  <data> &lt;p&gt;Last Updated: Jan. 31, 2011 C.E.&lt;/p&gt;</data>
</top>
