<top> <data> [h1]Digital Pali Reader - Help File[/h1]</data>
<data>[h2][b]Contents:[/b][/h2]</data>
<data>[ol]</data>
<data>[li][a class="green" href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="document.getElementById('maf').scrollTop = document.getElementById('helpNintro').offsetTop;"]Introduction[/a][/li]</data>
<data>[li][a class="green" href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="document.getElementById('maf').scrollTop = document.getElementById('helpNnotes').offsetTop;"]Notes[/a][/li]</data>
<data>[li][a class="green" href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="document.getElementById('maf').scrollTop = document.getElementById('helpNusage').offsetTop;"]Usage[/a][ul]</data>
<data>[li][a class="green" href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="document.getElementById('maf').scrollTop = document.getElementById('helpNtipitaka').offsetTop;"]Tipitaka Lookup[/a][/li]</data>
<data>[li][a class="green" href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="document.getElementById('maf').scrollTop = document.getElementById('helpNbookmarks').offsetTop;"]Bookmarking[/a][/li]</data>
<data>[li][a class="green" href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="document.getElementById('maf').scrollTop = document.getElementById('helpNsearch').offsetTop;"]Text Search[/a][/li]</data>
<data>[li][a class="green" href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="document.getElementById('maf').scrollTop = document.getElementById('helpNdict').offsetTop;"]Dictionary[/a][/li]</data>
<data>[li][a class="green" href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="document.getElementById('maf').scrollTop = document.getElementById('helpNtech').offsetTop;"]Technical[/a][/li][/ul]</data>
<data>[li][a class="green" href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="document.getElementById('maf').scrollTop = document.getElementById('helpNmisc').offsetTop;"]Miscellany[/a][/li][ul]</data>
<data>[li][a class="green" href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="document.getElementById('maf').scrollTop = document.getElementById('helpNpermalinks').offsetTop;"]Permalinks[/a][/li]</data>
<data>[li][a class="green" href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="document.getElementById('maf').scrollTop = document.getElementById('helpNtools').offsetTop;"]Other Tools[/a][/li][/ul]</data>
<data>[li][a class="green" href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="document.getElementById('maf').scrollTop = document.getElementById('helpNgratitude').offsetTop;"]Gratitude[/a][/li]</data>
<data>[li][a class="green" href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="document.getElementById('maf').scrollTop = document.getElementById('helpNfinal').offsetTop;"]Final Words[/a][/li]</data>
<data>[/ol]</data>
<data>[hr]</data>
<data>[div id="helpNintro" class="huge"]Introduction[/div]</data>
<data>[p]The Digital Pali Reader (DPR) is a tool, much like a hard-copy language reader, facilitating study of the Pali language at an advanced level. It contains the entire Myanmar version of the Pali tipitaka, as well as commentaries and sub-commentaries where available. It also includes the Visuddhimagga, Abhidhammatthasangaha and several ancient grammatical texts composed in Pali, all available for analysis and translation. Rather than offering a translation for the text being read, the DPR is like an ordinary text reader, which will normally include a dictionary with all of the difficult words found in the reader. The DPR differs from an ordinary reader in several respects:[/p]</data>
<data>[ol]</data>
<data>[li]The DPR allows for instant lookup of words, simply by clicking on a word in the passage being read. This avoids time spent looking for the word in a hard-copy dictionary or in another place on one's computer.[/li]</data>
<data>[li]The DPR has a built in search function similar to that of the CSCD. Whereas the CSCD allows for only global searches or searches of entire pitakas, the DPR provides great flexibility in searching multiple sets, multiple books, and multiple hierarchies of texts, as well as allowing advanced regular expression searches.[/li]</data>
<data>[li]The dictionary files in the DPR were not designed specifically for the purpose at hand, and word-to-definition matches are sometimes incorrect due to imperfect analysis.[/li]</data>
<data>[li]The DPR includes several dictionaries: Pali-English, Pali proper names, Concise Pali-English Dictionary and Concise English-Pali Dictionary.  There is also a searchable compilation of terms discussed in the commentaries and sub-commentaries, a title search for all books, and built-in search of accesstoinsight.org, either via the website or the off-line archive. All these can be directly accessed from the control panel under the "Dictionary" section. [/li]</data>
<data>[li]The DPR has a number of useful auxiliary features, including: [ul]</data>
<data>[li]bookmark and quote clipboard for keeping important passages, and a history to keep track of recently viewed passages.[/li]</data>
<data>[li]Permalinks to each paragraph and search query for referencing passages and terms for other DPR users.[/li]</data>
<data>[li]links to and searching of [a class="green" href="http://www.accesstoinsight.org/"]AccessToInsight.org[/a]'s list of translations[/li]</data>
<data>[li]a Pali conversion utility that converts to and from Velthius and Unicode scripts[/li]</data>
<data>[li]transliteration of Pali into Thai, Devanagari, Myanmar and Sinhala scripts [/li]</data>
<data>[li]conjugation tables via the CPED and analysis bar[/li]</data>
<data>[li]a Pali language quiz to test your vocabulary and a declension quiz to test your grammar[/li]</data>
<data>[li]random English quotes from Buddhavacana, by S. Dhammika[/li]</data>
<data>[/ul][/li]</data>
<data>[/ol]</data>
<data>[p]While the DPR is far from perfect, it is sure to be useful for intermediate Pali students who wish to advance their studies to a higher level.[br]</data>
<data>[/p]</data>
<data>[hr]</data>
<data>[div id="helpNnotes" class="huge"]Notes:[/div]</data>
<data>[ul]</data>
<data>[li]The reader was created for my own personal use, but anyone is welcome to use or distribute what I have made for their own benefit or the benefit of others. [/li]</data>
<data>[li]You will need at least a basic unicode font to view the Pāḷi characters properly.  If the word Pāḷi in this sentence shows up correctly, you are probably okay.  Otherwise, you'll have to do a search for "Unicode Font" on the Internet, and probably tell the DPR to use that font in the settings screen (press the "%" button).  The default font is "Tahoma", which should display the characters correctly.  For alternative scripts, it gets a little bit more difficult, and YMMV.  I use [a href="http://scripts.sil.org/cms/scripts/page.php?site_id=nrsi&amp;id=Padauk" style="color:green"]the Padauk font[/a] for Burmese and it works well.  The rest of the scripts should work with any standard unicode font containing that script (google "Thai unicode font", etc.).  There may be errors in the conversion still, so please send me (copy and paste in an email) any strange-looking words in regards to the alternative scripts.[/li]</data>
<data>[li]You will also need a recent version of [a href="http://www.getfirefox.com/"]Mozilla Firefox[/a].  I am currently working with Firefox 4, so there may be some problems with Firefox 3 that I am not aware of.  Many stylistic elements will not display properly in Firefox 3, for example.[/li]</data>
<data>[li]Text entry fields accept either unicode Pali characters or characters based on the [a style="color:green" href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="helpXML('velthuis.xml')"]Velthuis[/a] scheme. [/li]</data>
<data>[li]The reader was created for my own personal use, but anyone is welcome to use or distribute what I have made for their own benefit or the benefit of others. [/li]</data>
<data>[li]For the latest version of the reader, please visit [a style="color:green" href="http://pali.sirimangalo.org/"]pali.sirimangalo.org[/a][/li]</data>
<data>[li]</data>
<data>If any problem arises in the functioning of the reader, just press F5 to reset the reader[/li]</data>
<data>[li]</data>
<data>Many common tasks are now mapped to keys, which may be used instead of the buttons themselves, as follows:[br]</data>
<data>[ul]</data>
<data>[li]</data>
<data>[b]1,2,3[/b] for the three views (RAD)[/li]</data>
<data>[li]</data>
<data>[b]p,g,n[/b] for opening the previous, current (g) and next sections [/li]</data>
<data>[li]</data>
<data>[b]d,c,t[/b] for the three tools in the bottom frame [/li]</data>
<data>[li]</data>
<data>[b]x[/b] to open/close the control panel [/li]</data>
<data>[li]</data>
<data>[b]s[/b] to send selected text to the convertor, or the entire section if no text is selected.[/li]</data>
<data>[li]</data>
<data>[b],[/b] and [b].[/b] to go back and forth between dictionary entries (PED and DPPN).[/li]</data>
<data>[li]</data>
<data>[b]%,!,#,*,?,@[/b] for each of the six buttons at the bottom (see below).[/li]</data>
<data>[/ul]</data>
<data>[/li]</data>
<data>[/ul]</data>
<data>[hr]</data>
<data>[div id="helpNusage" class="huge"]Usage[/div]</data>
<data>[p]The left side of the screen contains the main controls. Basic use should require little explanation. What follows is a brief explanation of all of the controls in the control panel, by section:[/p]</data>
<data>[div id="helpNtipitaka" class="large"]Tipitaka Lookup[/div]</data>
<data>[p]The top three sections on the control panel are for browsing through the tipitaka and ancillary works.  At the top, there is the list of collections and books.  Below that is a set of hierarchical lists of the sections for the current book.  Below that, there are four sets of buttons: [/p]</data>
<data>[p][span id="RM" class="abut lbut" title="Maximize Read Frame (1)"]R[/span][span id="AM" class="abut mbut" title="Restore Frames (2)"]A[/span][span id="DM" class="abut rbut" title="Maximize Dictionary Frame (3)"]D[/span] </data>
<data>These buttons change the layout of the reader. "R" shows only the section being read with the small panel at the bottom, "A" shows the standard analysis view, and "D" maximizes the dictionary frame.[/p]</data>
<data>[p][span class="abut lbut" title="Retrieve previous section (p)"]&lt;[/span][span class="abut mbut" title="Retrieve current section (g)"]go[/span][span class="abut rbut" title="Retrieve next section (n)"]&gt;[/span] </data>
<data>These buttons load the actual text. "Go" brings up the current section, and the others bring up the previous and next sections in the current book.[/p]</data>
<data>[p][span id="difoutM" class="abut lbut sbut" title="Show Dictionary Frame (d)"]D[/span][span id="cofM" class="abut mbut" title="Show Convertor Frame (c)"]C[/span][span id="scfM" class="abut rbut"  title="Show Textpad Frame (t)"]T[/span] 
</data>
<data>These buttons switch what is shown in the bottom left frame. "D" shows the dictionary frame, "C" shows the text converter, and "T" shows the text pad.[/p]</data>
<data>[p][span id="dhierm" class="abut lbut sbut"]M[/span][span id="dhiera" class="abut mbut" title="Change to Aṭṭhakathā"]A[/span][span id="dhiert" class="abut rbut" title="Change to Ṭīkā"]T[/span] </data>
<data>These buttons change the hierarchy of texts to be studied. "M" switches to the root canonical text, "A" to the commentary, and "T" to the subcommentary.  Note that once a section has been retrieved, there will be buttons to the left of the title for the corresponding section in the other two hierarchies, if available.[/p]</data>
<data>[p]Once you have retrieved a section, it will display in the main window.  The title is at the top, with related sections in Mula, Atthakatha and Tika, to the left and translations (if enabled) to the right.  The title itself is a hyperlink, containing the permalink to this page.  If you are using Firefox 4 or higher, this will also show in the address bar.  See the section on [a href="#permalinks"]permalinks[/a] for more information.  Clicking on any word in the text brings up an analysis of the word and hopefully at least one (hopefully correct) definition from one of the three dictionaries.[/p]</data>
<data>[p]Below the buttons is a drop-down box with a history of previously viewed sections (max. 100).  Clicking on an entry retrieves that section, moving it to the top of the history list.[/p]</data>
<data>[div id="helpNbookmarks" class="large"]Bookmarking[/div]</data>
<data>[p]The DPR allows saving bookmarks for later reference.  All bookmark files are saved in your firefox profile folder under "DPR".  The ""Bookmarks" section of the control panel allows access to and manipulation of stored sections.  Clicking on the title "Bookmarks" opens up an advanced bookmark manager where you can view/add descriptions, change names, and delete bookmarks, as well as edit or clear the history (see above).  Below the title there is a drop-down list of saved bookmarks and a button [span class="abut obut small" title="Load this bookmark"]&gt;[/span]. To open a saved bookmark, including the scrolled distance, select a bookmark from the list and click on the [span class="abut obut small" title="Load this bookmark"]&gt;[/span] button.[br][br] The second row contains a text field and a button [span class="abut obut small" title="Set Bookmark"]S[/span]. To create a bookmark for the current page and scrolled distance, type in a name for the bookmark and click on the [span class="abut obut small" title="Set Bookmark"]S[/span] button. As an option, if you first select some text, that text will be added to the bookmark in the bookmark list.[/p]</data>
<data>[div id="helpNsearch" class="large"]Text Search[/div]</data>
<data>[p]The DPR has a built-in text search function that allows flexible search of the tipitaka and ancillary texts, via the "Text Search" section of the control panel.  There are many search options available, based on two variables: 1) whether you wish to search multiple sets, multiple books in the current collection, or the current book; and 2) whether you wish to search the current hierarchy or multiple hierarchies.  There is also an option ("Translations" in the drop-down menu) to access the [a class="green" href="http://www.accesstoinsight.org/"]AccessToInsight.org[/a] Google custom search, or the off-line archive (if installed and linked via the options page) to search their English translations.[/p][p]If you wish to search within the current set, book, or hierarchy, first navigate to the appropriate place using the corresponding lists and buttons.  If you are searching multiple collections or the Tipitaka, they will have no effect. [/p][p] Next, enter the string for which to search (or multiple strings seperated by the "+" sign) and then select a search type from the dropdown (set at "Tipitaka" by default).  You will notice that various options appear based on the type of search you choose.  Check the appropriate boxes, and then click the [span class="abut obut small" title="Search for word"]&gt;[/span].  The search window will open (use the [span class="abut obut small"  title="Minimize search frame"]-[/span] / [span class="abut obut small"  title="Maximize search frame"]+[/span] button to minimize / maximize the search frame) and search results will begin to appear, with words containing the search term(s) at the top, followed by a list of paragraphs with the matched search term(s) highlighted.  There is a stop button [img src="images/stop.png" width=24] that allows you to interrupt the search if necessary. [/p][p]Once the search is complete, clicking on a search term will cause the reader to show only paragraphs containing that term.  To show all results again, click the "x" beside the current word (in a box on the top right of the search frame, when viewing a single matched word).  Clicking on the span class="abut obut small"]go[/span]  button beside a paragraph will open the containing section, minimizing the search frame (which can be opened again via the [span class="abut obut small"  title="Maximize search frame"]+[/span] button).[/p][p]The "RegEx" checkbox allows javascript regular expressions to be used in the search (use with care!).[/p][p] To search for a page number, use the following syntax: P1.0001, P1.0002, etc., where "P" (or V, M, T) is the PTS pagination set, the first "1" is the volume, and the following (must be four digits) is the page number.[/p]</data>
<data>[div id="helpNdict" class="large"]Dictionary[/div]</data>
<data>[p]The dictionary lookup has nine options, some with advanced options available by clicking "adv". "DPR" runs an analysis on the word or passage at hand as it normally would. This only works for full words and phrases. "PED" searches the Pali-English Dictionary, "DPPN" the Dictionary of Pali Proper Names, "CPED" the Concise Pali-English Dictionary, and "CEPD" the Concise English-Pali Dictionary.  "Aṭṭha" (Aṭṭhakathā) and "Ṭīkā", search through words or phrases explained in the commentaries and sub-commentaries respectively.  "Title" gives a list of matching titles in all books.[/p][p]  [a name="advdict" /][b]Advanced Dictionary options:[/b][p]Each dictionary has its own set of advanced options, some in common, some unique.  All are explained here:[/p][ul]</data>
<data>[li][b]Reg. Exp.:[/b]  Allows javascript regular expressions to be used in the dictionary search.[/li] </data>
<data>[li][b]Fuzzy:[/b] This option allows you to ignore diacritics in your search.  This equates long and short vowels, and ignores dots and the tilde.[/li] </data>
<data>[li][b]Full Text:[/b] Only for PED and DPPN, this allows full-text search, rather than just entry search.[/li] </data>
<data>[li][b]Start of Word Only:[/b] Enabled by default for the dictionaries, this limits the search to matches at the beginning of the word.  To search within entries, uncheck this.[/li] </data>
<data>[p]If search-as-you-type is enabled in the option screen (see below), the results will be shown as you type.  Otherwise, you will have to press the [span class="abut obut small" title="Edit or look up a word"]&gt;[/span] button to execute the search. If you choose "PED" and type "aa" into the box, for example, it will come up with a list of Pali-English Dictionary entries starting with a long "ā".  All lookup functions except DPR allow inner-word search and javascript-type regular expressions (wildcards) in advanced options.  Note that these disable search-as-you-type.[/p]</data>
<data>[div id="helpNtech" class="large"]Technical[/div]</data>
<data>[p] The last set of buttons on the control panel has some technical buttons:[/p][p]</data>
<data>[span class="abut lbut small" title="Set configuration"]%[/span]</data>
<data>[span class="abut rbut small" title="Reset configuration"]![/span] These buttons allow one to adjust the layout and colors of the reader as well as other misc. options, as follows:[/p][ul]</data>
<data>[li][b]Layout:[/b]  Specify the height of the dictionary frame and width of control panel in pixels, as well as background colors of each.[/li] </data>
<data>[li][b]Text:[/b] Specify colors, either by name or HTML code ("black" is the same as "#000" and "#000000).  Specify font family for the text, size of the normal text and the script to be used for reading the texts.[/li] </data>
<data>[li][b]Options:[/b] [ul]</data>
	<data>[li]"Show translations" adds links to translations from accesstoinsight.org as well as ancient-buddhist-texts.org, if available.  If you have downloaded the ATI offline archive, you can specify the location here, which will also enable off-line ATI search.[/li] </data>
	<data>[li]"Dictionary search as you type" causes the dictionaries to start outputting results as you type.  Otherwise, pressing "Enter" or clicking the ">" button is required.[/li][/ul]</data>
	<data>[li]"Show in text" allows you to show or hide permalinks after each paragraph.[/li][/ul]</data>
<data>[/li][/ul]</data>	
<data>[p] [span class="abut lbut small" title="Pali Quiz"]#[/span]</data>
<data>[span class="abut rbut small" title="Quote of the Moment"]*[/span] The "#" button opens a set of Pali quizes to test your vocabulary and grammar. The "*" button displays a random quote from the book, Buddhavacana.[/p][p]</data>
<data>[span class="abut lbut small" title="Help (New Window)"]?[/span]</data>
<data>[span class="abut rbut small" title="Send Feedback"]@[/span] "?" shows this help file and "@" allows you to contact me via email.[/p]</data>
<data>[hr]</data>
<data>[div id="helpNmisc" class="huge"]Miscellany[/div]</data>
<data>[div id="helpNpermalinks" class="large"]Permalinks:[/div]</data>
<data>[p]A DPR permalink is a special URL that, when entered in the Firefox address bar or clicked from a hyperlink (provided the DPR is installed), goes directly to the place it refers to, showing the results of a search, if specified.  The permalink to a given section may be accessed three ways: via the address bar URL, which changes (requires Firefox 4 or higher) based on the current location, the dhamma wheel ([span class="pointer hoverShow" title="Click to copy permalink to clipboard"]☸[/span]) to the right of the section title, and the dhamma wheels to the left of each paragraph.  Clicking on a dhamma wheel causes the link to be copied to the clipboard for further use.  The dhamma wheel after each paragraph adds the paragraph number to the link.  An example permalink is:[br][br][a class="green" href="chrome://digitalpalireader/content/index.htm?loc=d.0.0.0.0.0.0.m&amp;para=4&amp;query=bhagavaa+bhikkhave"]chrome://digitalpalireader/content/index.htm?loc=d.0.0.0.0.0.0.m&amp;amp;para=4&amp;query=bhagavaa+bhikkhave[/a][br][br]  The link is made up of up to four parts, depending on the information it contains: first, everything before the question mark is the actual location of the DPR itself; second, the information between the "loc=" and the first ampersand (&amp;) is the location of the section in DPR syntax, in this case the first section of the Digha Nikaya (d), mula (m); third, "para=4" tells the DPR to scroll to the fourth paragraph; fourth, "query=bhagavaa+bhikkhave" tells the DPR to highlight the words "bhagavaa" and "bhikkhave".  This link can be shared with other DPR users for easy reference, or even placed on a website or forum, as in the following example: [br][br]([a class="green" href="chrome://digitalpalireader/content/index.htm?loc=d.0.0.0.0.0.0.m&amp;para=4&amp;query=bhagavaa+bhikkhave"]Link to paribbājakakathā[/a])[br][br][/p]</data>
<data>[div id="helpNtools" class="large"]Other Tools:[/div]</data>
<data>[p]Finally, there are some hidden tools in the DPR; hidden because I didn't kow where to put them. Links to them will be placed here:[br][br]</data>
<data>[a href="etc/grammar/GMD/index.html" style="color:green" target="_blank"]A Practical Grammar of the Pali Language by Charles Duroiselle[/a][br][br]</data>
<data>[a href="etc/grammar/cheet.html" style="color:green" target="_blank"]Pali Cheet Sheet by Alan McClure[/a]</data>
<data>[/p]</data>
<data>[hr]</data>
<data>[div id="helpNgratitude" class="huge"]Gratitude:[/div]</data>
<data>[p]Thanks first and foremost to Alexander Genaud, without whom I would still be pulling my hair out (figuratively) waiting for the script to load a single section. Without his initial help there would be no DPR. Without his later advice we would still be accessing one paragraph at a time and the data would be pre-analyzed and thus difficult to read. There would also be no search function. Special thanks also to Alan McClure, Ven. Gavesako, Peter Masefield, Lin Qian, Leland George, and Ven. Khemaratana for spotting errors in the script and offering encouragement and suggestions. Thanks to Upaasako, our first team member who helped with the bookmarking system among other things. Thanks to John Bullit for his link on [a href="http://www.accesstoinsight.org/outsources/pali.html" style="color:green"]www.accesstoinsight.org[/a] as well as for graciously hosting a PHP script providing the list of sutta translations used by the DPR, as well as a way to link the DPR to the offline ATI archive. And thanks to everyone else who helped out in the project in any small or large way - sotthi vo hotu. Special impersonal credit is due to all of those people involved in creating and providing publicly-available electronic versions of the following resources:[br]</data>
<data>[ul]</data>
<data>[li]The Myanmar Pali Tipitaka[/li]</data>
<data>[li]The Pali English Dictionary[/li]</data>
<data>[li]Concise Pali English Dictionary[/li]</data>
<data>[li]Concise English Pali Dictionary[/li]</data>
<data>[li]Dictionary of Pali Proper Names[/li]</data>
<data>[li]PaliLookup[/li]</data>
<data>[li]Buddha Vacana[/li]</data>
<data>[/ul]</data>
<data>[p]Should this software infringe upon anyone's felt right to forbid the copying of any of the above or other materials, I apologize for the felt violation. I am sorry to know that some people feel this way about generally useful things that benefit the public immensely when distributed freely. May all be happy and well. [hr]</data>
<data>[div id="helpNfinal" class="huge"]Final Words:[/div]</data>
<data>[p]1) Please write to me with errors, bugs, spiders, etc. My email is [a style="color:green" href="mailto:yuttadhammo@gmail.com"]yuttadhammo@gmail.com[/a]. [/p]</data>
<data>[p]2) Please check our [a style="color:green" href="http://pali.sirimangalo.org/"]weblog[/a] for new updates.[/p]</data>
<data>[p]Best wishes and good luck,[/p]</data>
<data>[p]Yuttadhammo[/p]</data>
<data>[p]Last Updated: Mar 31, 2011 C.E.[/p]</data> </top> 
