<?xml version="1.0"?>
<xml>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Uttaramūla Nikāya[/div][p]One of the fraternities of monks in Ceylon, an off-shoot of the Abhayagiri sect.  Their headquarters were probably at the Uttarola Vihāra, built by King Mānavamma, and given to the monks of the Abhayagiri Vihāra, for having consented to take into the Order his elder brother, in spite of the fact that he had lost one eye as the result of some yoga practices.  [/p][p]The first chief of Uttarola was the king's brother himself and he was in charge of six hundred monks.  He was granted great honours and privileges together with five classes of servants to minister to him.  He was also appointed to supervise the guardians of the Tooth Relic (Cv.lvii.7-11, and 16-26; also Geiger's Trs.i.194, n.2 and 3).  [/p][p]From a Tamil inscription of Mānavamma we find that he kept up his patronage of the Uttaramūla Nikāya, and it is recorded that he gave over the custodianship of the Tooth Relic to a monk of this fraternity, named Moggallāna (Epi.  Zey., vol.ii., pt.  vi., pp.250ff).[/p][p]Anuruddha, author of the Anuruddha Sataka and the Abhidhammattha-Sangaha, describes himself in the colophon to the former work as an "Upasthavira" of the Uttaramūla Nikāya.[/p][p]In later years this Nikāya produced many an illustrious star in Celyon's literary firmament, among them the grammarian Moggallāna, Vilgammūla, Mahā Thera and Sri Rāhula.  For details about them see P.L.C., passim.[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Uttama[/div][hr][p]1. Uttama.-Author of the Bālāvatāra-tīkā and the Lingatthavivaranatīkā.  He was a native of Pagan.  Gv.63, 73; see also Bode, op.  cit., 22 and n.1.[/p][p][/p][p]2. Uttama.-The name given to a cetiya connected with Sikhī Buddha.  Āsanatthavika Thera, in a previous birth, came across this cetiya while wandering in the forest and did obeisance to it.  Ap.i.255.[/p][p][/p][p]3. Uttama.-A general of Mānābharana.  He was defeated at Vacāvātaka by Rakkha.  Cv.lxx.295.[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Uddhanadvāra[/div][p]A village in Rohana.  There the Ādipāda Vikkama-bāhu gained a victory.  (Cv.lxi.16, 25).  It was in the region called Atthasahassa, and Sirivallabha, who reigned over this district, made Uddhanadvāra his capital.  The village formed one of the centres of battle in the campaign of Parakkamabāhu I.  (Cv.lxxiv.86, 113; lxxv.182. For its identification see Cv.Trs.i.29, n.4).[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Unnanābhī[/div][p]A spider, as big as a chariot wheel, which lived in a cave in Mount Cittakūta.  During the rains the geese who lived on the mountain entered his cave for shelter.  Every month the spider would make a web, each thread of which was as thick as a cow's halter, at the entrance of the cave.  At the end of the rains a young goose, who had been given two portions of food to make him strong would break the web and the geese would fly away.  Once the rains lasted five months and the geese, having no food, were forced to eat their eggs and then their young.  When the time came for them to fly away, none of them were strong enough to break the web and the spider sucked the blood of them all.  That was the end of the Dhatarattha geese.  J.v.469-70.[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Uttaroliya[/div][p]A village in Ceylon, in Rājarattha.  Near it was Uttaroliyavāpi.  The Rasavāhinī has a story of a cowherd boy of the village who gave his rice cake to a pindaptāika-thera.  The monk developed arahantship before eating it.  In his next birth the boy was born in the same village.  By virtue of his merit, a treasure trove appeared in the lake, which no one could get except his mother.  The king heard of it, and, having tested the truth of the story, gave it to the boy.  Ras.ii.22f.[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Upāli [/div][hr][p][b]1. Upāli Thera.[/b]-One of the most eminent of the Buddha's immediate disciples.  He belonged to a barber's family in Kapilavatthu and entered the service of the Sākiyan princes.  When Anuruddha and his cousins left the world and sought ordination from the Buddha at Anupiyā Grove, Upāli accompanied them.  They gave him all their valuable ornaments, but, on further consideration, he refused to accept them and wished to become a monk with them.  The reason given for his refusal is that he knew the Sākyans were hot-headed, and feared that the kinsmen of the princes might suspect him of having murdered the young men for the sake of their belongings.[/p][p]At the request of the Sākiyan youths, the Buddha ordained Upāli before them all, so that their pride might be humbled.  (Vin.ii.182; DhA.i.116f; see also Bu.i.61; but see BuA.44; the Tibetan sources give a slightly different version, see Rockhill, op.  cit., pp.  55-6; according to the Mahāvastu iii.179, Upāli was the Buddha's barber, too).  [/p][p]Upāli's upajjhāya was Kappitaka (Vin.iv.308).  When Upāli went to the Buddha for an exercise for meditation, he asked that he might be allowed to dwell in the forest.  But the Buddha would not agree, for if Upāli went into the forest he would learn only meditation, while, if he remained amongst men, he would have knowledge both of meditation and of the word of the Dhamma.  Upāli accepted the Buddha's advice and, practising insight, in due course won arahantship.  The Buddha himself taught Upāli the whole of the Vinaya Pitaka (ThagA.i.360f, 370; AA.i.172).[/p][p]In the assembly of the Sangha, the Buddha declared him to be the most proficient of those who were learned in the Vinaya (vinayadharānam) (A.i.24; see also Vin.iv.142, where the Buddha is mentioned as speaking Upāli's praises).  He is often spoken of as having reached the pinnacle of the Vinaya, or as being its chief repository (Vinaye agganikkhitto), (E.g., Dpv.iv.3, 5; v.7, 9) and three particular cases - those of Ajjuka (Vin.iii.66f), the Bhārukacchaka monk (Vin.iii.39) and Kumāra-Kassapa (AA.i.158; MA.i.336; J.i.148; DhA.iii.145) - are frequently mentioned in this connection as instances where Upāli's decisions on Vinaya rules earned the special commendation of the Buddha.  In the Rājagaha Council, Upāli took a leading part, deciding all the questions relative to the Vinaya, in the same way as Ananda decided questions regarding the Dhamma (Vin.ii.286f; DA.i.11f; Mhv.iii.30).[/p][p]In accordance with this tradition, ascribing to Upāli especial authority regarding the rules of the Order, various instances are given of Upāli questioning the Buddha about the Vinaya regulations.  Thus we find him consulting the Buddha as to the legality or otherwise of a complete congregation performing, in the absence of an accused monk, an act at which his presence is required (Vin.i.325f).  Again, he wishes to know if, in a matter which has caused altercations and schisms among members of the Order, the Sangha declares re-establishment of concord without thorough investigation, could such a declaration be lawful? (Vin.i.358f).  When a monk intends to take upon himself the conduct of any matter that has to be decided, under what conditions should he do so? What qualities should a monk possess in himself before he takes upon himself to warn others? (Vin.ii.248f).  In what case can there be an interruption of the probationary period of a monk who has been placed on probation? (Vin.ii.33f).[/p][p]A whole list of questions asked by Upāli and answers given by the Buddha on matters pertaining to the Vinaya rules is found in the chapter called Upāli-Pañcaka in the Parivāra (Vin.v.180-206; see also the Upālivagga of the Anguttara Nikāya v.70ff).[/p][p]It is not possible to determine which of these and other questions were actually asked by Upāli, and which were ascribed to him on account of his traditional reputation.[/p][p]It is said (E.g., Vin.iv.142; Sp.iv.876) that even in the Buddha's lifetime monks considered it a great privilege to learn the Vinaya under Upāli.  The monks seem to have regarded Upāli as their particular friend, to whom they could go in their difficulties.  Thus, when certain monks had been deprived by thieves of their clothes, it is Upāli's protection that they seek (Vin.iii.212; see also the story of Ramanīyavihārī, ThagA.i.116).[/p][p]The canon contains but few records of any discourses connected with Upāli, apart from his questions on the Vinaya.  In the Anguttara Nikāya (A.iv.143f) he is mentioned as asking the Buddha for a brief sermon, the Buddha telling him that if there were anything that did not conduce to revulsion and detachment, Upāli could be sure that such things did not form part of the Buddha's teaching.  There is a record of another sermon (A.v.201ff) which the Buddha is stated to have preached when Upāli expressed the desire to retire into the solitude of the forest.  The Buddha tells him that forest-life is not for the man who has not mastered his mind or attained to tranquillity.[/p][p]For other sermons see Upāli Sutta and Ubbāhika Sutta.[/p][p]Three verses are ascribed to Upāli in the Theragāthā (vv.  249-51; but see Gotama the Man, p.215; another verse ascribed to Upāli, but so far not traced elsewhere, is found in the Milinda p.108) where he admonishes the brethren to seek noble friends of unfaltering character, to learn the monks' code of discipline and to dwell in solitude.[/p][p]In the time of Padumuttara, Upāli was a very rich brahmin named Sujāta.  When the Buddha came to his father's city in order to preach to him the Dhamma, Sujāta saw him, and in the assembly be noticed an ascetic named Sunanda, holding over the Buddha for seven days a canopy of flowers.  The Buddha declared that Sunanda would, in the time of Gotama Buddha, become famous as the Elder Punna Mantānī-putta.  Sujāta, too, wished to seethe future Buddha Gotama, and having heard Padumuttara praise the monk Pātika as chief of the Vinayadharas, he wished to hear, regarding himself, a similar declaration from Gotama.  With this end in view he did many deeds of merit, chief of which was the erection of a monastery named Sobhana, for the Buddha and his monks, at an expense of one hundred thousand.[/p][p]As a result he was born in heaven for thirty thousand kappas and was one thousand times king of the devas.  One thousand times, too, he was cakkavatti.[/p][p]Two kappas ago there was a Khattiya named Añjasa, and Upāli was born as his son Sunanda.  One day he went to the park riding an elephant named Sirika, and met, on the way, the Pacceka Buddha Devala, whom he insulted in various ways.  Sunanda was, thereupon, seized with a sensation of great heat in his body, and it was not till he went with a large following to the Pacceka Buddha and asked his pardon that the sensation left him.  It is said that if the Buddha had not forgiven him, the whole country would have been destroyed.  This insult paid to the Pacceka Buddha was the cause of Upāli having been born as a barber in his last birth (Ap.i.37ff).[/p][p]Buddhaghosa says (Sp.i.272, 283) that while the Buddha was yet alive Upāli drew up certain instructions according to which future Vinayadharas should interpret Vinaya rules, and that, in conjunction with others, he compiled explanatory notes on matters connected with the Vinaya.[/p][p]In direct pupillary succession to Upāli as head of the Vinayadharas was Dāsaka, whom Upāli had first met at the Valikārāma, where Upāli was staying (Mhv.v.10).  Upāli taught him the whole of the Vinaya.[/p][p]Upāli's death was in the sixth year of Udāyibhadda's reign.  Dpv.v.7ff.[/p][hr][p][b]2. Upāli.[/b]-A lad of Rājagaha.  His parents, wishing him to live a life of ease, did not have him instructed in any of the usual means of livelihood, lest he should be inconvenienced while learning them.  After much consideration, they decided to have him ordained.  He joined the Order with sixteen other companions equally young, and it is said that they rose at dawn and started shouting for food.  This was the reason for the rule that no one under twenty years of age should receive the upasampadā ordination.  Vin.i.77f.[/p][hr][p][b]3. Upāli Thera.[/b]-The Apadāna (i.91f) contains the story of a thera named Upāli, who is to be distinguished from the eminent disciple of that name, though the Apadāna verses obviously point to a confusion of the legends of the two.  The Apadāna Commentary distinguishes this monk as "Bhāgineyya Upāli," and states that he was a nephew of the Venerable Upāli.  He was born in Kapilavatthu and was ordained by his uncle, who later became an arahant.[/p][p]Bhāgineyya Upāli had been a householder in the time of Padumuttara.  Later he left the world and became an ascetic in Himavā.  There he met the Buddha and the monks, and uttered their praises in song.  As a result he was eighteen times king of the devas and twenty-five times king of men.[/p][hr][p][b]4. Upāli.[/b]-Distinguished as [b]Upāli- [a name="Gahapati"]Gahapati[/a][/b].  He lived at  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/n/naalandaa,Nālandā')"]Nālandā[/a] and was a follower of  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/n/nigantha_nataputta,Nigantha Nātaputta')"]Nigantha Nātaputta[/a].  [/p][p]He was present when  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/d/diighatapassii,Dīgha-Tapassī')"]Dīgha-Tapassī[/a] reported to Nātaputta an account of his visit to the  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/b/buddha,Buddha')"]Buddha[/a] in the  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/pa/pavarika,Pāvārika')"]Pāvārika[/a] Mango-grove.  Upāli undertook to go himself to the Buddha and refute his views, in spite of the protestations of Dīgha-Tapassī.  At the end of his discussion with the Buddha, which is recorded in the  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/u/upaali_s,Upāli Sutta')"]Upāli Sutta[/a], Upāli is converted and invites the Buddha to a meal.  Although the Buddha enjoins upon Upāli that his benefactions to the Niganthas should not cease because of his conversion, Upāli gives instructions that no Nigantha be admitted to his presence, but that if they need food it shall be given to them.  Hearing a rumour of his conversion, first Tapassī, and later Nātaputta himself, go to Upāli's house, where they learn the truth.  When Nātaputta is finally convinced that Upāli has become a follower of the Buddha, hot blood gushes from his mouth (M.i.371ff).  [/p][p]According to  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/b/buddhagosa,Buddhaghosa')"]Buddhaghosa[/a] (MA.ii.621, 830), Nātaputta had to be carried on a litter to  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/pa/pava,Pāvā')"]Pāvā[/a], where he died shortly after.[/p][p]Upāli became a  [a href="http://www.palikanon.com/english/wtb/s_t/sotaapanna,Sotāpanna')"]Sotāpanna[/a] (MA.ii.620).[/p][p]He is mentioned, with  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/aa/aananda,Ananda')"]Ananda[/a], [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/c/citta,Citta-gahapati')"]Citta-gahapati[/a],  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/d/dhammika,Dhammika-upāsaka')"]Dhammika-upāsaka[/a] and  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/ku/khujjuttaraa,Khujjuttarā')"]Khujjuttarā[/a], as one who had acquired the four Patisambhidā while being yet a learner (sekha).  Vsm.ii.442; VibhA.388.[/p][hr][p][b]5. Upāli Thera.[/b]-Head of the chapter of monks sent from Siam, at the request of Kittisirirājasīha, to re-establish the Upasampadā ordination in Ceylon.  He was held in great esteem by the king of Ceylon and often preached to him.  Upāli died in Ceylon of an incurable disease of the nose, and his funeral obsequies were held with great solemnity.  Cv.c.71, 94, 117, 127, 142.[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Ummāda-Cittā[/div][p]Mother of Pandukābhaya, king of Ceylon.  She was the daughter of Bhaddakaccānā and Panduvāsudeva, and when she was born the brahmins foretold that her son would kill all his uncles.  Her brothers, therefore, resolved to kill her, but she was saved by her eldest brother Abhaya.  She was put in a chamber built on a single pillar, with an entrance through the king's bedroom.  But Dīghagāmanī fell in love with her and visited her at night with the help of a hook-ladder.  Later, when with child, she was given to him in marriage (Mhv.ix.1ff; Dpv.x.4).[/p][p]She was given the name of Ummāda-Cittā because the mere sight of her beauty drove men mad.  Mhv.ix.5.[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Uttiya or Uttika Sutta[/div][hr][p]1. Uttiya or Uttika Sutta.-Uttiya Thera visits the Buddha and asks him for an explanation of the five sensual elements (kāmagunā) mentioned by him.  The Buddha explains them, and declares that they should be abandoned in order that the Noble Eightfold Path might be cultivated.  S.v.22.[/p][p][/p][hr][p]2. Uttiya or Uttika Sutta.-Uttiya asks the Buddha for a teaching in brief, on which he might meditate while dwelling in solitude.  The Buddha tells him that he must purify "the rudiments in good states" (ādim eva visodhehi kusalesu dhammesu), and proceeds to mention the four satipatthānas.  As a result of developing the latter Uttiya became an arahant.  S.v.166.[/p][p][/p][hr][p]3. Uttiya or Uttika Sutta.-The Paribbājaka Uttiya visits the Buddha and asks him his views regarding the eternity of the world, the end of the world, the identity of body and soul, and the continuation of the existence of the Tathāgata after death.  The Buddha replies that he teaches nothing about such things, but that the object of his teaching is to enable beings to realise emancipation.  Thereupon Uttiya asks the Buddha whether the world is led to follow that teaching.  The Buddha remains silent.  Ananda, wishing to prevent any misunderstanding on the part of Uttiya, explains that there is no "leading," but that the Buddha knows that all those who escape from the world do so along a certain path, just as the gate-keeper of a well-guarded town knows that whoever enters that town must, inevitably, use the one entrance.  A.v.193-5.[/p][p][/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Ullabhakolakannikā[/div][p]Evidently a village in Ceylon.  A woman of this village, having learnt that the Thera Dīghabhānaka-Abhaya was reciting the Ariyavamsa-patipāda, went all the way to hear him, a distance of five leagues, nursing her baby the while.  She arrived at the vihāra and, having laid the baby down, listened to two preachers.  Earlier in the day, when Abhaya Thera, having finished a portion of the sermon, was about to take some refreshment, she censured him, saying that he should have refreshed himself earlier.  The thera agreed and finished the sermon and, at the last word, the woman became a sotāpanna.  AA.i.386.[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Upāsaka Vagga[/div][hr][p]1. Upāsaka Vagga.-The second chapter of the Brāhmana Samyutta.  S.i.172ff.[/p][hr][p]2. Upāsaka Vagga.-The eighteenth chapter of the Pañcaka Nipāta of the Anguttara Nikāya; on various matters, chiefly connected with laymen.  A.iii.203-18.[/p][hr][p]3. Upāsaka Vagga.-The tenth chapter of the Dasaka Nipāta of the Anguttara Nikāya.  A.v.176-206.[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Upasāgara[/div][p]Son of Mahāsāgra, who was the king of Uttaramadhurā.  [/p][p]Upasāgara's elder brother was Sāgara, and when their father died, Upasāgara became his brother's viceroy.  Having been suspected of an intrigue in the king's zenana, he fled to the court of Upakamsa in  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/ay/asitanjana,Asitañjano')"]Asitañjano[/a].  There he fell in love with  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/d/devagabbhaa,Devagabbhā')"]Devagabbhā[/a], and when she was with child he married her and they lived in Govadhamāna.  [/p][p]Their children were the notorious  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/ay/andhakavenhu_puttaa,Andhakavenhu-dāsaputtā')"]Andhakavenhu-dāsaputtā[/a].[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Ussillya-Tissa Thera[/div][p]He was a resident of the Abhayagiri-vihāra.  When the monks of this vihāra tried to introduce the Vaitulya heresy, he refused to be associated with them and went, with a few others, to Dakkhinagiri-vihāra.  There they formed the Sāgaliya sect under a monk named Sāgala.  P.L.C.66.[/p]</e>
  <e/>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Uttarapañcāla[/div][p]A city.  When  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/ay/apacara,Apacara')"]Apacara[/a] (Upacara), king of Ceti, was swallowed up by the fires of  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/ay/aviici,Avīci')"]Avīci[/a], because of his falsehood, his five sons came to the brahmin Kapila and sought his protection.  He advised them to build new cities.  The city built by the fourth son was called Uttarapañcāla.  It was founded in the north of Ceti, on the spot where the prince saw a wheel-frame (cakkapañjara) entirely made of jewels (J.iii.461).  [/p][p]According to the scholiast to the  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/ka/kaamaniita_jat_228,Kāmanīta Jātaka')"]Kāmanīta Jātaka[/a] (J.ii.214), however, and also according to the [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/ku/kumbhakaara_jat_408,Kumbhakāra Jātaka')"]Kumbhakāra Jātaka[/a] (J.iii.379ff), Pañcāla or Uttarapañcāla is the name of a country (rattha) whose capital was Kampilla, while in the  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/b/brahmadatta_jat_323,Brahmadatta Jātaka')"]Brahmadatta Jātaka[/a] (iii.79) also in the scholiast of the  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/c/citta_sambhuuta_jat_498,Citta-Sambhūta Jātaka')"]Citta-Sambhūta Jātaka[/a] (iv.396), Uttarapañcāla is given as the name of the city and Kampilla as that of the country and we are told that a king Pañcāla reigned there.[/p][p]Pañcāla was also the name of the king of Uttarapañcāla in the  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/sa/sattigumba_jat_503,Sattigumba Jātaka')"]Sattigumba Jātaka[/a] (iv.430), the [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/j/jayaddisa_jat_513,Jayaddisa Jātaka')"]Jayaddisa Jātaka[/a] (v.21), and the  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/g/gandatindu_jat_520,Gandatindu Jātaka')"]Gandatindu Jātaka[/a] (v.98).  In all these Uttarapañcāla is spoken of as a city in Kampilla.  In the  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/maha/mahaummagga_jat_546,Mahā Ummagga Jātaka')"]Mahā Ummagga Jātaka[/a] (vi.391ff), Culani Brahmadatta is the king of Uttarapañcāla.[/p][p]In the  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/s/somanassa_jat_505,Somanassa Jātaka')"]Somanassa Jātaka[/a] (J.iv.444), mention is made of a city named Uttarapañcāla in the Kuru country, with Renu as its king.  Whether the reference is to a different city it is not possible to say.  See also  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/pa/pancala,Pañcāla')"]Pañcāla[/a].[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Ujjhānasaññikā[/div][p]The name given to a group of devas who once visited the Buddha at Jetavana late at night.  They charged the Buddha with inconsistency, but later, begging his forgiveness, they were pardoned by him (S.i.23-5).  Buddhaghosa (SA.i.50f ) says that they did not belong to any separate deva-world but were given this name by the Theras of the Council on account of their captious remarks.  They had heard the Buddha praise his monks for self-denying practices while he himself wore raiment of silk, fine cloth or linen, ate food worthy of a rājā, dwelt in a Fragrant Cell like unto a deva-mansion and used good medicines.[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Ugga Sutta[/div][hr][p]1. Ugga Sutta.-Records the conversation between the Buddha and Ugga (2) (q.v.), minister of King Pasenadi.  A.iv.6-7.[/p][p][/p][p]2. Ugga Sutta.-Deals with the eight wonderful qualities of Ugga of Vesalī.  See Ugga (5).[/p][p]A.iv.208-12.[/p][p][/p][p]3. Ugga Sutta.-Deals with the eight wonderful qualities of Ugga of Hatthigāmaka.  See Ugga (4).  A.iv.212-6.[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Uttara[/div][hr][p][b]1. Uttara.[/b]-A thera.  He was the son of an eminent brahmin of Rājagaha (of Sāvatthi, according to the Apadāna).  He became proficient in Vedic lore and renowned for his breeding, beauty, wisdom and virtue.  The king's minister, Vassakāra, seeing his attainments, desired to marry him to his daughter; but Uttara, with his heart set on release, declined, and learnt the Doctrine under Sāriputta.  Later he entered the Order and waited on Sāriputta.[/p][p]One day Sāriputta fell ill and Uttara set out early to find a physician.  On the way he set down his bowl by a lake and went down to wash his mouth.  A certain thief, pursued by the police, dropped his stolen jewels into the novice's bowl and fled.  Uttara was brought before Vassakāra who, to satisfy his grudge, ordered him to be impaled.  The Buddha, seeing the ripeness of his insight, went to him and placing a gentle hand, "like a shower of crimson gold," on Uttara's head, spoke to him and encouraged him to reflection.  Transported with joy and rapture at the Master's touch, he attained sixfold abhiññā and became arahant.  Rising from the stake, he stood in mid-air and his wound was healed.  Addressing his fellow-celibates, be told them how, when he realised the evils of rebirth, he forgot the lesser evil of present pain (Thag.vv.121-2; ThigA.i.240ff).[/p][p]In the time of Sumedha Buddha, he bad been a Vijjādhara.  Once, while flying through the air, he saw the Buddha at the foot of a tree in the forest and, being glad, offered him three kanikāra flowers.[/p][p]By the Buddha's power, the flowers stood above him forming a canopy.  The Vijjādhara was later born in Tāvatimsa, where his palace was known as Kanikāra.[/p][p]He was king of the gods one hundred and five times, and king of men one hundred and three times.[/p][p]According to the Apadāna (quoted in ThigA.), he became an arahant at the age of seven.  This does not agree with the rest of the story and is probably due to a confusion with some other Uttara.[/p][p]Uttara is probably to be identified with Tīnikpikārapupphiya of the Apadāna.  Ap.ii.441ff.  Ras.i.52f.[/p][hr][p][b]2. Uttara.[/b]-A thera.  He was the son of a brahmin of Sāketa.  While on some business at Sāvatthi, he saw the Twin Miracle and, when the Buddha preached the Kālakārāma Sutta at Sāketa, he entered the Order.  He accompanied the Buddha to Rājagaha and there became an arahant (Thag.vv.161-2; ThagA.i.283f).[/p][p]During the time of Siddhattha Buddha he had been a householder and became a believer in the Buddha.  When the Buddha died, he called together his relations and together they paid great honour to the relics.[/p][p]He is evidently identical with Dhātupūjaka of the Apadāna (ii.425).[/p][p]It is probably this thera who is mentioned in the Uttara Sutta (A.iv.162ff).[/p][hr][p][b]3. Uttara[/b].-A devaputta who visits the Buddha at the Anjanavana in Sāketa.  He utters a stanza, and the Buddha, in another stanza, amplifies what he has said.  S.i.54.[/p][hr][p][b]4. Uttara.[/b]-A thera.  At the time of the  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/va/vajjiputtakaa,Vajjian')"]Vajjian[/a] heresy, he was the attendant of the Elder  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/r/revata,Revata')"]Revata[/a] and had been twenty years in the Order.  The Vajjians of Vesāli went to him and, after much persuasion, succeeded in getting him to accept one robe from them.  [/p][p]In return for this he agreed to say before the Sangha that the Pācīnaka Bhikkhus held the true Doctrine and that the Pātheyyaka monks did not.  Thereafter Uttara went to Revata, but Revata, on hearing what he had done, instantly dismissed him from attendance upon him.  When the Vesāli monks were informed of the occurrence, they took the nissaya from Uttara and became his pupils.  Vin.ii.302-3; Mhv.iv.30.[/p][hr][p][b]5. Uttara[/b].-An arahant.  He, with Sona, was sent by Asoka, at the conclusion of the Third Council, to convert Suvannabhūmi.  They overcame the female demon and her followers, who had, been in the habit of coming out of the sea to eat the king's sons, and they then recited the Brahmajāla Sutta.  Sixty thousand people became converts, five hundred noblemen became monks and fifteen hundred women of good family were ordained as nuns.[/p][p]Thenceforth all princes born in the royal household were called Sonuttara.  Mhv.iv.6; 44-54; Sp.i.68f; Mbv.115; The Dipavamsa speaks of Sonuttara as one person (viii.10).[/p][hr][p][b]6. Uttara.[/b]-A brahmin youth (Uttara-mānava), pupil of Pārāsariya.  He once visited the Buddha at Kajaligalā in the Mukheluvana and the Buddha preached to him the Indriya-bhāvanā Sutta (M.iii.298ff).[/p][p]Perhaps it is this same mānava that is mentioned in the Pāyāsi Sutta.  When Pāyāsi Rājañña was converted by Kumāra Kassapa, he instituted almsgiving to all and sundry, but the gifts he gave consisted of such things as gruel and scraps of food and coarse robes.  Uttara, who was one of his retainers, spoke sarcastically of Pāyāsi's generosity, and on being challenged by Pāyāsi to show what should be done, Uttara gave gladly and with his own hands excellent foods and garments.  As a result, after death, while Pāyāsi was born only in the empty Serisakavimāna of the Cātummahārājika world, Uttara was born in Tāvatimsa.  D.ii.354-7; see also VvA.297f.  where the details are slightly different.[/p][hr][p][b]7. Uttara[/b].-A youth of Kosambī, son of a minister of King Udena.  When his father died, the youth was appointed by the king to carry out certain works in the city which his father had left unfinished.[/p][p]One day, while on his way to the forest to fell timber, he saw Mahā Kaccana and, being pleased with the thera's demeanour, went and worshipped him.  The thera preached to him, and the youth invited him and his companions to a meal in his house.  At the conclusion of the meal Uttara followed Mahā Kaccāna to the vihāra and asked him to have his meals always at his house.  He later became a Sotāpanna and built a vihāra.  He persuaded most of his relations to join in his good deeds, but his mother refused to help and abused the monks.  As a result she was born in the peta-world.  (See Uttaramātā).  PvA.140ff.[/p][hr][p][b]8. Uttara.[/b]-A brahmin youth.  When Erakapatta, king of the Nāgas, offered his daughter's hand to anyone who could answer his questions - hoping thereby to hear of a Buddha's appearance in the world - Uttara was among those who aspired to win her.  The Buddha, wishing for the welfare of many beings, met Uttara on his way to the Nāga court and taught him the proper answers to the questions.  At the end of the lesson, Uttara became a Sotāpanna.  When he repeated the answers before the Nāga maiden, Erakapatta was greatly delighted and accompanied him to the Buddha, who preached to him and to the assembled multitude.  DhA.iii.230ff.[/p][hr][p][b]9. Uttara.[/b]-A pupil of Brahmāyu.  He was sent by his teacher from Mithilā to Videha, to find out if the Buddha bore the marks of the Super man.  Having made sure of the presence of all the thirty-two marks on the Buddha's person, he dogged the Buddha's footsteps for seven months, in order to observe his carriage in his every posture.  At the end of that period, he returned to Brahmāyu and reported what he had seen (M.ii.134ff; SnA.i.37).  Buddhaghosa says (MA.ii.765) that Uttara became known as Buddhavīmamsaka-mānava on account of his close watch over the Buddha.[/p][hr][p][b]10. Uttara.[/b]-A youth, evidently a personal attendant of Pasenadi.  The Buddha taught him a stanza to be recited whenever the king sat down to a meal.  The stanza spoke of the merits of moderation in eating.  DhA.iv.17; but see S.i.81-2 for a different version of what is evidently the same incident.  There the youth is called Sudassana.[/p][hr][p][b]11. Uttara.[/b]-A royal prince to whom Konāgamana Buddha preached at Surindavatī on the full-moon day of Māgha.  He later became the Buddha's aggasāvaka.  Bu.xxiv.22; BuA.215; J.i.43.[/p][hr][p][b]12. Uttara.[/b]-Younger brother of Vessabhū Buddha.  The Buddha preached his first sermon to Uttara and Sona at the Aruna pleasaunce near Anupama.  Later Uttara became the Buddha's aggasāvaka.  Bu.xxii.23; BuA.205; J.i.42; D.ii.4.[/p][hr][p][b]13. Uttara.[/b]-Son of Kakusandha Buddha in his last birth.  Bu.xxiii.17.[/p][hr][p][b]14. Uttara.[/b]-The name of the Bodhisatta in the time of Sumedha Buddha.  He spent eighty crores in giving alms to the Buddha and the monks and later joined the Order.  J.i.37-8; Bu.xii.11.[/p][hr][p][b]15. Uttara.[/b]-A khattiya, father of Mangala Buddha.  Bu.iv.22; J.i.34.[/p][hr][p][b]16. Uttara[/b].-Son of Padumuttara Buddha in his last birth (Bu.xi.21).  He was the Bodhisatta.  SA.ii.67; DA.ii.488; but see J.i.37 and Bu.xi.11, where the Bodhisatta's name is given as the Jatila Ratthika.[/p][hr][p][b]17. Uttara.[/b]-Nephew of King Khallatanāga of Ceylon.  He conspired with his brothers to kill the king, and when the plot was discovered committed suicide by jumping on to a pyre.  MT.612.[/p][hr][p][b]18. Uttara.[/b]-A banker, a very rich man of Sāvatthi.  He had a son, designated as Uttara-setthi-putta, whose story is given in the Vattaka Jātaka.  J.i.432ff.[/p][hr][p][b]19. Uttara.[/b]-The city in which Mangala Buddha was born.  Bu.iv.22; J.i.34.[/p][hr][p][b]20. Uttara.[/b]-The city of King Arindama.  Revata Buddha preached there to the king and the assembled multitude.  BuA.133.[/p][hr][p][b]21. Uttara[/b].-A township (nigama), near which Revata Buddha spent seven days, wrapt in meditation.  At the conclusion of his meditation, the Buddha preached to the assembled multitude on the virtues of nirodhasamāpatti.  BuA.133-4. This may be the same as No.  20.[/p][hr][p][b]22. Uttara.[/b]-One of the palaces occupied by Paduma Buddha before his Renunciation.  Bu.ix.17.[/p][hr][p][b]23. Uttara.[/b]-A township of the Koliyans.  Once, when the Buddha was staying there, he was visited by the headman Pātaliya.  v.l.  Uttaraka.  S.iv.340.[/p][hr][p][b]24. Uttara.[/b]-A nunnery built by King Mahāsena.  Mhv.xxxvii.43.[/p][hr][p][b]25. Uttara.[/b]-A general of Moggallāna I.  Cv.xxxix.58.[/p][hr][p][b]26. Uttara.[/b] A padhānagara built by Uttara (25).[/p][hr][p][b]27. Uttara.[/b]-A minister of Sena I.  He built in the Abhayuttara Vihāra a dwelling-house called Uttarasena.  Cv.l.83.[/p][hr][p][b]28. Uttara[/b].-A thera who, with sixty thousand others, came from the Vattaniya hermitage in the Vindhyā forest to be present at the foundation ceremony of the Mahā Thūpa in Anurādhapura.  Mhv.xxix.40; Dpv.xix.6.[/p][hr][p][b]29. Uttara[/b].-A banker of Uttaragāma, father of Uttarā (13).  BuA.116.[/p][hr][p][b]30. Uttara.[/b]-An ājivaka who offered eight handfuls of grass to Mangala Buddha for his seat.  BuA.116.[/p][hr][p][b]31. Uttara.[/b] See  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/b/bherapaasaana_vih,Bherapāsāna Vihāra')"]Bherapāsāna Vihāra[/a].[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Uddālaka Jātaka (No.  487)[/div][p]The story of Uddālaka given above.  It was related in reference to a monk who led a deceitful life.  [/p][p][/p][p]The monk is identified with Uddālaka.  (J.iii.232).  [/p][p][/p][p]The Jātaka is depicted in the Bhārhūt Tope (see Cunningham, Plate XLVI).[/p][p][/p][p]On the same occasion were preached the Makkata, Kuhaka and Setaketu Jātakas.[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Upavāna Sutta[/div][hr][p]1. Upavāna Sutta.-The conversation referred to above, between Upavāna and Sāriputta, on the antakara.  A.ii.163f.[/p][p][/p][p]2. Upavāna Sutta.-The Buddha explains to Upavāna the arising of sorrow (dukkha-samuppāda).  S.ii.41f.[/p][p][/p][p]3. Upavāna Sutta.-The Buddha explains, in answer to a question of Upavāna, how the Dhamma is immediate in its results (sanditthika).  S.iv.41f.[/p][p][/p][p]4. Upavāna Sutta.-The conversation referred to above, between Sāriputta and Upavāna, where the latter explains how the bojjhangas conduce to a happy life.  S.v.76f.[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Udakadāyaka Thera[/div][hr][p]1. Udakadāyaka Thera.-An arahant.  In a former birth he saw the Buddha Siddattha having his meal and brought him a pot of water.  Sixty-one kappas ago he became a king named Vimala (Ap.i.205).  He is probably identical with Sānu Thera.  ThagA.i.115.[/p][p][/p][p]2. Udayadāyaka Thera.-An arahant.  In a previous birth he filled a vessel of water for Padumuttara Buddha.  As a result, he could find water in any spot he wished (Ap.ii.437).  His Apadāna-verses are found in the Theragāthā Commentary under the names of two theras: Mahā Gavaccha (i.57) and Gangātīriya (i.249).[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Uttarapāla[/div][p]A thera.  He was the son of a brahmin in Sāvatthi.  When he had attained to years of discretion he saw the Twin Miracle and entered the Order.  One day, amid desultory recollection, he was beset by sensual desires, but after a violent mental struggle, he arrested his evil thoughts and attained arahantship.[/p][p][/p][p]In the time of Vipassī Buddha, he had made a bridge for the Buddha to cross (Thag.252-4; ThagA.i.371f).[/p][p]He is evidently identical with Setudāyaka of the Apadāna (ii.408).[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Udena Vatthu[/div][p]The story cycle of King Udena, in many respects the most interesting of all the stories of the Dhammapada Commentary (DhA,i.161-231).  [/p][p][/p][p]It consists of six stories of diverse origin and character, dealing with the fortunes of the king, his three queen-consorts and his treasurer.  [/p][p]Only two of the stories are really concerned with Udena, the rest being introduced by familiar literary devices.  Versions of each of the six stories occur in the writings of Buddhaghosa, indicating that they go back to a common source.  [/p][p][/p][p]Parallels to one or more stories are also to be found in the Divyāvadāna, the Kathāsaritsāgara and other Sanskrit collections and in the Tibetan Kandjur.  [/p][p]For an analysis of the cycle and its parallels see Burlinghame, Bud.  Legends, i., pp.51 and 62ff.[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Ulumpa[/div][p]A township of the Sākyans.  The Buddha once stayed there and was visited by Pasenadi, king of Kosala, who felt remorse for the murder of his general Bandhula.  The king went alone inside the Gandhakuti, laying aside the symbols of royalty which he left with his minister Dīgha-Kārāyana.  When the king came out, he found that all his followers had gone, leaving behind only one horse and a serving-woman.  On learning that Vidūdabha had been made king, Pasenadi left for Rājagaha, to seek the help of Ajātasattu, and died outside the city-gates.  J.iv.151f; DhA.i.356. See also Medatalumpa.[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Uttari (-manussadhamma) Sutta[/div][p]There are six things without getting rid of which it is impossible to obtain qualities of a transcendental nature (uttarimanussadhammā), to say nothing of Ariyan insight and wisdom.  [/p][p][/p][p]Those things are forgetfulness, want of discrimination, lack of control of the senses, intemperance in eating, deceitfulness and prattle.  A.iii.430.[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Uggāhamāna-Samana-Mandikāputta[/div][p]A Paribbājaka.  Once when he was staying near Sāvatthi in Mallikā's pleasance at the Samayappavādaka hall, the carpenter (thapati), Pañcakanga, on his way to see the Buddha, visited him and had a conversation with him, which conversation Pañcakanga later reported to the Buddha (M.ii.22f).  The details are given in the Samana-Mandikā Sutta.[/p][p]According to Buddhaghosa (MA.ii.710), the Paribbājaka's original name was Sumana, but he was called Uggāhamāna because he had the ability to learn a few things (because he was always learning things?).[/p][p]Chalmers (Further Dialogues ii.12n) suggests that perhaps his mother's name was originally Sumanā and that it was altered to Samanā, just as there is the further tendency to read mundikā for the second part, in order to make her name mean "shaveling recluse" on familiar Pāli analogy.[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Ussada[/div][p]A Niraya.  It resembled a city with four gates and a wall.  Mittavindaka, arriving at Ussaka in his wanderings, saw there a man supporting a wheel as sharp as a razor, which to Mittavindaka appeared like a lotus-flower.  Mittavindaka took it from him, and realising then what it was, tried to escape, but was unsuccessful.  This was the suffering undergone by those who had smitten their mothers.  Sakka, during a visit to Ussaka, saw Mittavindaka, but could do nothing for him (J.iv.3f; iii.206f).[/p][p]Ussada was considered a place of great suffering (E.g., J.iv.403), and also a place where those who, having promised a gift fail to give it, are born (J.iv.405).  Once the Bodhisatta was born in Ussada, for cruelty during his reign as king of Benares, and he suffered for eighty thousand years (J.vi.2).  Beings born there have their tongues pierced with glowing hooks and are dragged about on a floor of heated metal (J.vi.112).[/p][p]In the scholiast to the Matakabhatta Jātaka (J.i.168) reference is made to sixteen Ussada-nirayā.[/p][p]Revatī (q.v.) was once cast into Ussada-niraya.  VvA.223.[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Upanisā Sutta[/div][hr][p]1. Upanisā Sutta.-On causal association.  S.ii.29f.[/p][p][/p][p]2. Upanisā Sutta.-On how, to the wicked man, the possibilities of all high attainments are destroyed, not so to the man who is righteous.  A.v.313f.[/p][p][/p][p]3. Upanisā Sutta.-The same as 2, but the Sutta is ascribed to Sāriputta.  A.v.315f.[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Ucchitthabhatta Jātaka (No.  212)[/div][p]In a village near Kāsī, a brahmin's wicked wife received her lover when her husband was away.  She prepared a meal for her lover and while he ate she stood at the door watching for her husband.  The brahmin appearing before he was expected, the lover was bundled into the store-room.  The woman put some hot rice over the food left unfinished by her lover and gave the plate to her husband.  When asked why the rice was hot on the top and cold at the bottom, she remained silent.  The Bodhisatta, who had been born as a poor acrobat, had been at the door of the house waiting for alms and had seen all that had happened.  He informed the brahmin of his wife's conduct and both wife and lover received a sound beating.[/p][p]The story was told to a monk who hankered after his wife.  The Buddha related the story in order to show him that in a past birth this same wife had made him eat the leavings of her paramour.  J.ii.167ff.[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Udāna[/div][p]A short collection of eighty stories, in eight vaggas, containing solemn utterances of the Buddha, made on special occasions.  The Udāna proper, comprising the Buddha's utterances, is mostly in verse, in ordinary metres (Sloka, Tristubh, Jagatī), seldom in prose (E.g., iii.10; viii.1, 3, 4).  Each Udāna is accompanied by a prose account of the circumstances in which it was uttered.  [/p][p]The book forms the third division of the Khudda-kanikāya (DA.i.17; but see p.15, where it is the seventh).  [/p][p]Udāna is also the name of a portion of the Pitakas in their arrangement according to matter (anga).  Thus divided, into this category fall eighty-two suttas, containing verses uttered in a state of joy (DA.i.23-4; see also UdA.  pp.2-3).  [/p][p]The prose-and-verse stories of the Udāna seem to have formed the model for the Dhammapada Commentary (See Bud.  Legends, i.28).  [/p][p]The Udāna is also the source of twelve stories of the same Commentary and contains parallels for three others.  About one-third of the Udāna is embodied in these stories.  See, ibid., i.47-8, for details.[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Udumbaraphaladāyaka Thera[/div][p]An arahant.  In the time of Vipassī Buddha he was a householder.  [/p][p][/p][p]Meeting the Buddha walking along the bank of the river Vinatā, he plucked some figs and gave them to him (Ap.i.295).[/p][p][/p][p]He is probably identical with Paccaya Thera.  See ThagA.i.341.[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Udāyī Sutta[/div][hr][p]1. Udāyī Sutta.-A conversation between Ananda and Udāyī in the Ghositārāma at Kosambī.  Ananda explains how the Buddha has proved that not only the body but even consciousness is without self.  S.iv.166f.[/p][p][/p][p]2. Udāyī Sutta.-Udāyī visits the Buddha at Desaka (?) in the Sumbha country and describes how he had realised Nibbāna by developing the bojjhangas.  S.v.89f.[/p][p][/p][p]3. Udāyī Sutta.-Ananda reports to the Buddha that Udāyī preached to a very large following of laymen.  The Buddha says that this is not an easy thing to do; he who preaches to a large audience must see, (1) that his talk has a logical reference, (2) that it has reasoning (pariyāya), (3) that it is inspired by kindness (dayā), (4) that it is not for worldly gain, (5) that it causes pain to no one.  A.iii.184.[/p][p][/p][p]4. Udāyī Sutta.-The Buddha asks Udāyī (Lāludāyī according to the Commentary) as to what are the topics of recollection.  Three times he asks the question, but Udāyī sits silent.  The Buddha then says he knew Udāyī was a fool, and puts the question to Ananda, who explains five such topics connected with the jhānas.  A.iii.322-5.[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Uddesavibhanga Sutta[/div][p]The Buddha utters the brief statement that a monk should always so guard his mind that it may not be externally diffused nor internally set.  The monks repeat this statement to Mahā Kaccāna, who gives a detailed exposition thereof.  When the Buddha is told of Kaccāna's explanation, he praises his erudition (M.iii.223ff).[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Upajjhā Sutta[/div][p]A monk goes to his teacher and confesses to him the difficulty he experiences in living the celibate life profitably.  The teacher takes him to the Buddha, who suggests to him a different way of conduct.  The monk acts according to the Buddha's advice and becomes an arahant.  On being informed of this, the Buddha makes it a topic for a sermon.  A.iii.69-71.[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Upassaya Sutta[/div][p]Ananda, with great difficulty, persuades Mahā Kassapa to accompany him to a settlement of nuns.  Mahā Kassapa goes and preaches to them, but Thulla-Tissā, not being pleased with the sermon, upbraids Mahā Kassapa for what she calls his impertinence in preaching when Ananda is present.  "How does the needle-pedlar deem he could sell a needle to the needle-maker?" Kassapa is upset, and Ananda asks for forgiveness in the nun's name, for women, he says, are foolish, and one must be indulgent to them.  Kassapa reminds the audience that it was he himself and not Ananda who was declared by the Buddha to be the Buddha's equal in the attainment of the jhānas.  S.ii.214.[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Ummāpupphiya Thera[/div][hr][p]1. Ummāpupphiya Thera.-An arahant.  In a past birth when a festival was being held in honour of the thūpa erected over the relics of Siddhattha Buddha, be placed an ummā-flower on the thūpa.  Nine kappas ago he became king eighty-five times under the name of Somadeva (Ap.i.172).[/p][p]He is probably identical with Cakkhupāla Thera.  See ThagA.i.196.[/p][p][/p][p]2. Ummāpupphiya Thera.-An arahant.  In a past birth he saw the Buddha Siddhattha wrapt in samādhi and offered him, in homage, azure (ummā-) flowers, which formed a canopy above the Buddha's head.  Later, Ummāpupphiya was born in Tusita.  Fifty-five kappas ago he was a king called Samantacchadana.  Ap.i.258.[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Udumbara[/div][hr][p]1. Udumbara.-A thera of Makuva, author of a tīkā on the Petakopadesa.  Gv.75, 65.[/p][p][/p][p]2. Udumbara.-A village.  Revata went there from Kannakujja and stopped there before proceeding to Aggalapura and Sahajāti.  Thither the Elders followed him to ask his opinion on the Vajjian heresy.  Vin.ii.299.[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Uddhagāma[/div][hr][p]1. Uddhagāma.-A district (?) in Ceylon.  It contained the village of Vasabha, which was given to the Jetavana Vihāra by Mahānāga (Cv.xli.97).[/p][p][/p][p]2. Uddhagāma.-A village in Rohana.  The forces of Parakkamabāhu I, carried on a campaign there for three months (Cv.lxxiv.92).[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Uposatha[/div][hr][p][b]1. Uposatha.[/b]-King, son of Varakalyāna and an ancestor of the Sākyan tribe.  His son was Mandhātā (Dpv.iii.4).  He was one of the kings at the beginning of the kappa (J.ii.311; iii.454).  In the Dīgha Commentary (DA.i.258) he is given as the son of Varamandhātā and the father of Cara.  In the northern texts he is called Uposadha.  Mtu.i.348; Divy.210.[/p][hr][p][b]2. Uposatha.[/b]-The name of the Elephant-Treasure of the  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/c/cakkavatti,Cakkavatti')"]Cakkavatti[/a] [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/maha/mahasudassana_s,Mahāsudassana')"]Mahāsudassana[/a].  He was "all white, sevenfold firm (sattappatittha), wonderful in power, flying through the sky." (D.ii.174; M.iii.173f).  In the Lalita Vistara his name is given as Bodhi.[/p][p]Uposatha is also the name of a tribe of elephants, the ninth in a series of ten tribes, of ascending importance (DA.ii.573; UdA.403).  It is said that a cakkavatti's elephant belongs either to the Chaddanta tribe or to the Uposatha.  If a Chaddanta elephant comes to a cakkavatti, it is the youngest of the tribe that comes, if an Uposatha elephant, then it will be the foremost (DA.ii.624; J.iv.232, 234; KhA.172).  When the cakkavatti dies, the elephant goes back to his fellows (DA.ii.635).  The strength of an Uposatha elephant is equal to that of one thousand million men (BuA.37).  In the Milindapañha (p.282), the king of the Uposatha elephants is described as being gentle and handsome, eight cubits in height and nine in girth and length, chewing signs of rut in three places on his body, all white, sevenfold-firm.  Just as this elephant could never be put into a cow-pen or covered with a saucer, so could no one keep as slaves the children of Vessantara.[/p][hr][p][b]3. Uposatha.[/b]-Known as Uposatha-kumāra.  The eldest of the ninety nine brothers of Samvara, king of Benares.  When Samvara ascended the throne, his brothers protested and laid siege to his city; but Uposatha, having discovered by means of questions put to Samvara, that he was in character by far the best suited for kingship, persuaded the others to renounce their claims to the throne.  Uposatha is identified with Sāriputta.  J.iv.133ff.[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Uddālaka[/div][p]Son of the Bodhisatta (then chaplain of the king of Benares) and a slave-girl, whom he first met in the royal park.  The boy was so called because he was conceived under an uddāla-tree.  When grown up he went to Takkasilā and later became leader of a large company of ascetics.  In the course of their travels he and his followers came to Benares, where they received great favours from the people.  Attracted by his reputation, the king once visited him with the royal chaplain.  On that occasion Uddālaka arranged that he and his followers should feign to be very holy men given up to various austerities.  The chaplain, seeing through their dishonesty and discovering the identity of Uddālaka, persuaded him to leave his asceticism and become chaplain under him (J.iv.298-304).[/p]</e>
  <e/>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Udāyibhadda (Udāyibhaddaka)[/div][p]Son of Ajātasattu.  When Ajātasattu, after the death of his father, paid his first visit to the Buddha and saw the Buddha seated amidst the monks in a scene of perfect calm and silence, his first thought was: "Would that my son, Udāyibhadda, might have such calm as this." (D.i.50).  [/p][p][/p][p]Buddhaghosa explains (DA.i.153) this thought by saying that Ajātasattu feared that his son might follow his own example and kill him as he had killed his own father.  His fears were justified, for he was killed by his son Udāyibhadda, who reigned for sixteen years.  [/p][p][/p][p]The latter, in his turn, was killed by his son Anuruddhaka (Mhv.iv.1ff.  According to Dvy.  his son was Munda).  [/p][p][/p][p]It was in Udāyibhadda's eighth year that Vijaya, king of Ceylon, died, and in his fifteenth year that Panduvasudeva came to the throne (Sp.i.72).  The Dīpavamsa (iv.38; v.97; xi.8) calls him Udaya and the Mahābodhivamsa (p.96), Udayabhadda.  See also Kālāsoka.[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Ucchanga Jātaka (No.  67)[/div][p]Three men who were ploughing on the outskirts of a forest were mistaken for bandits and taken before the king.  While they were being tried a woman came to the palace and with loud lamentations begged for "wherewith to be covered." The king ordered a shift to be given to her but she refused, saying that that was not what she meant.  The king's servants came back and reported that what the woman wanted was a husband.  When the king had her summoned and questioned, she admitted that it was so.  Being pleased with the woman, the king asked in what relationship the three prisoners stood to her.  She answered that one was her husband, one her brother and one her son.  When the king asked which of the three she wished to have released, she chose the brother, because, she said, the two others were replaceable.  Well pleased with her, the king released all three.[/p][p][/p][p]The story was related in reference to a woman in a village in Kosala who obtained, from the king of Kosala, the release of three men in similar circumstances and in the same way.  J.i.306-8.[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Uppaladāyika Therī[/div][p]Thirty-one kappas ago she was the wife of the Khattiya Aruna of Arunavatī.  One day, being filled with anguish that she had not done any good deed which would bring her a happy condition of rebirth, she begged her husband for a holy recluse on whom she could wait.  Her wish was granted, and she gave to the recluse a bowl of excellent food and perfume, the whole covered with a large robe.  As a result, she was born in Tāvatimsa and became for a thousand times the consort of the king of the devas.  Her body was always of the hue of the lotus and she had all womanly beauty.  In her last birth she was born in a Sākyan family and joined the Bodhisatta's court at the head of a thousand women.  Later, she left the world and became an arahant, seven days after joining the Order (Ap.ii.601-3).  A set of verses in which she sang the praises of the Buddha, appear at the end of the Apadāna account.  She is perhaps to be identified with Soma Therī.[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Upādiyamāna Sutta[/div][p]When asked by a certain monk to give a topic for reflection, the Buddha tells him that if a man clings, he is Māra's bondsman.  If he cling not, he is free.  The Buddha asks the monk what be understands by this and is pleased with the explanation.  The monk meditates on this and becomes an arahant.  S.iii.73f.[/p]</e>
  <e/>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Uttarārāma[/div][hr][p]1. Uttarārāma.-An image-house constructed by Parakkamabāhu I.  to the north of Pulatthipurā.  It was hewn out of the actual rock and had three grottoes, made by expert craftsmen - the Vijjādhara grotto, the grotto with the image in sitting posture and the grotto with the recumbent image.  Cv.lxxviii.74ff; for a description of it see Cv.  Trs.ii., 111, n.2; Bell: Arch.  Survey of Ceylon for 1907, pp.7ff.[/p][p][/p][p]2. Uttarārāma.-The monastery where Mangala Buddha held his second Great Assembly (Sannipāta) in the presence of his kinsmen.  BuA.120.[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Ujjuhāna[/div][p]A hill thickly covered with jungle and abounding in streams which get overfull during the rains and make living on the hill uncomfortable.[/p][p][/p][p]According to others, Ujjuhana is the name of a bird, capable of bearing cold and rain with comfort.  Thag.597; ThagA.i.536.[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Uruvela-Kassapa[/div][p]One of three brothers, the [b]Tebhātika-Jatilas[/b], living at  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/u/uruvelaa,Uruvelā')"]Uruvelā[/a].  He lived on the banks of the  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/n/neranjara,Nerañjarā')"]Nerañjarā[/a] with five hundred disciples.  Further down the river lived his brothers [b]Nadī-Kassapa[/b] with three hundred disciples and [b]Gayā-Kassapa[/b] with two hundred.  [/p][p]The Buddha visited Uruvela-Kassapa and took lodging for the night where the sacred fire was kept, in spite of Kassapa's warning that the spot was inhabited by a fierce  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/n/naaga,Nāga')"]Nāga[/a].  The Buddha, by his magical powers, overcame, first this Nāga and then another, both of whom vomited fire and smoke.  Kassapa being pleased with this exhibition of iddhi-power, undertook to provide the Buddha with his daily food.  Meanwhile the Buddha stayed in a grove near by, waiting for the time when Kassapa should be ready for conversion.  Here he was visited by the  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/c/caatummahaaraajikaa,Four Regent Gods')"]Four Regent Gods[/a],  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/sa/sakka,Sakka')"]Sakka[/a], Brahma and others.  The Buddha spent the whole rainy season there, performing, in all, three thousand five hundred miracles of various kinds, reading the thoughts of Kassapa, splitting firewood for the ascetics' sacrifices, heating stoves for them to use after bathing in the cold weather, etc.  Still Kassapa persisted in the thought, "The great ascetic is of great magic power, but he is not an arahant like me." Finally the Buddha decided to startle him by declaring that he was not an arahant, neither did the way he followed lead to arahantship.  Thereupon Kassapa owned defeat and reverently asked for ordination.  The Buddha asked him to consult with his pupils, and they cut off their hair and threw it with their sacrificial utensils into the river and were all ordained.  Nadī-Kassapa and Gayā-Kassapa came to inquire what had happened, and they, too, were ordained with their pupils.  At  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/g/gayaasiisa,Gayāsīsa')"]Gayāsīsa[/a] the Buddha preached to them the Fire Sermon ( [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/aa/aadittapariyaaya_s,Āditta-pariyāya')"]Āditta-pariyāya[/a]), and they all attained arahantship.[/p][p]From Gayāsīsa the Buddha went to  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/r/raajagaha,Rājagaha')"]Rājagaha[/a] with the Kassapas and their pupils, and in the presence of  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/b/bimbisara,Bimbisāra')"]Bimbisāra[/a] and the assembled populace Uruvela-Kassapa declared his allegiance to the Buddha.  This story of the conversion of the Kassapas is given in Vin.i.24ff and in AA.i.165f; also in ThagA.i.434ff.[/p][p]Later, in the assembly of monks, Uruvela-Kassapa was declared to be the chief of those who had large followings (aggam mahāparisānam) (A.i.25).  Six verses attributed to him are found in the Theragāthā (vv.375-80), wherein he reviews his achievement and relates how he was won over by the Buddha.[/p][p]In the time of Padumuttara Buddha he was a householder, and having seen the Buddha declare a monk (Sīhaghosa was his name, Ap.ii.481) to be the best of them with large followings, wished for himself to be so honoured in a future life, and did many works of merit towards that end.[/p][p]Later, he was born in the family of Phussa Buddha as his younger step-brother, his father being Mahinda.  (According to Bu.xix.14, Phussa's father was Jayasena).  He had two other brothers.  The three quelled a frontier disturbance and, as a reward, obtained the right to entertain the Buddha for three months.  They appointed three of their ministers to make all the arrangements and they themselves observed the ten precepts.  The three ministers so appointed were, in this age, Bimbisāra, Visākha and Ratthapāla.[/p][p]Having sojourned among gods and men, the three brothers, in their last birth, were born in a brahmin family, the name of which was Kassapa.  They learnt the three Vedas and left the household life (AA.i.165f; DhA.i.83ff; Ap.ii.481ff).[/p][p]According to the  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/maha/mahanaradakassapa_jat_544,Mahā-Nārada-Kassapa Jātaka')"]Mahā-Nārada-Kassapa Jātaka[/a] (J.vi.220ff; Ap.ii.483), Uruvela-Kassapa was once born as Angati, king of Mithilā in the Videha country.  He listened to the teachings of a false teacher called Guna and gave himself up to pleasure, till he was saved by his wise daughter Rujā, with the help of the Brahma Nārada, who was the Bodhisatta.[/p][p]Uruvela-Kassapa was so called partly to distinguish him from other Kassapas and partly because he was ordained at Uruvela.  At first he had one thousand followers, and after he was ordained by the Buddha all his followers stayed with him and each of them ordained a great number of others, so that their company became very numerous (AA.i.166).[/p][p]The scene of the conversion of Uruvela-Kassapa is sculptured in Sanchi.  According to Tibetan sources, Kassapa was one hundred and twenty years old at the time of his conversion (Rockhill, op.  cit., 40).  [/p][p] [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/h/hiuen_tsang,Hiouen Thsang')"]Hiouen Thsang[/a] found a stūpa erected on the spot where the Buddha converted Kassapa (Beal, Bud.  Records, ii.130).[/p][p] [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/b/belatthasisa_th,Belatthasīsa')"]Belatthasīsa[/a] was a disciple of Uruvela-Kassapa and joined his teacher when the latter was converted (ThagA.i.67).   [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/s/senaka,Senaka Thera')"]Senaka Thera[/a] was Kassapa's sister's son (ThagA.i.388). [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/va/vacchapaala_th,Vacchapāla')"]Vacchapāla[/a] was among those who joined the Order, after having seen Kassapa pay homage to the Buddha at Rājagaha (ThagA.i.159).[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Upatthāna Sutta[/div][hr][p]1. Upatthāna Sutta.-The Buddha asks Ananda if he considers that every kind of moral practice produces like results.  Ananda says they do not, and proceeds to explain his point of view.  The Buddha agrees with him, and when Ananda has gone away, tells the monks that though Ananda is yet a learner (sekha), it would not be easy to find his equal in insight.  A.i.225.[/p][p][/p][p]2. Upatthāna Sutta.-Five qualities which make an invalid difficult for anyone to look after, and the absence of which makes him a good patient.  A.iii.143-4.[/p][p][/p][p]3. Upatthāna Sutta.-On five qualities requisite for an attendant on the sick.  A.iii.144-5.[/p][p][/p][p]4. Upatthāna Sutta.-Record of a conversation between a deva and a monk who dwelt in a forest tract in Kosala.  During his siesta the monk would often fall asleep, and the deva, wishing his welfare and desiring to agitate him, draws near and asks him not to give himself up to somnolent habits.  The monk replies to the effect that once a man has obtained insight by the suppression of desire and lust, there is no need to plague himself with unnecessary exertions (S.i.197f).[/p][p]According to the Commentary (SA.i.232), the monk was an arahant.  He had far to go to procure food, and when he came back, tired out, he would bathe and rest.[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Ujjaya Sutta[/div][hr][p]1. Ujjaya Sutta.-Records the questions asked by the brahmin Ujjaya regarding sacrifice, and the Buddha's answer.  See above Ujjaya 3. A.ii.42.[/p][p][/p][p]2. Ujjaya Sutta.-Ujjaya's request to the Buddha (referred to above under Ujjaya 3) for a teaching which would bring him welfare in both worlds and the Buddha's reply thereto, detailing four qualities which would bring prosperity in this world - the accomplishments of exertion (utthānasampādā), and of protection (ārakkhasampadā), friendship with the good (kalyānamittatā), and regular living (samajīvitā) - and four others for bringing happiness in the next - viz., the four sampadā (accomplishments) of sīla (morality), citta (concentration and meditation), cāga (generosity), and paññā (higher wisdom).  A.iv.285-9.[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Upasampadā Vagga[/div][p]The sixteenth chapter of the Pañcaka Nipāta of the Anguttara Nikāya.  The suttas of this chapter deal with the qualities requisite for a monk who wishes to receive the upasampadā, to give nissaya, to institute a novice, to become an official in the Order, etc.  A.iii.271-8.[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Uggaha Sutta[/div][p]Preached at Bhaddiya to the daughters of Uggaha Mendakanattā just before their marriage.  A wife should rise betimes before her husband, and sleep after him; she should respect his wishes, give him pleasure and be of sweet speech.  His parents and elders and all those whom he holds in esteem, should she reverence and honour; she should be skilful in all the duties of the household; she should look after the servants in the house and supervise their duties, provide them with all necessaries and be kind and helpful to them; she should safeguard her husband's interests and look after his wealth; she should be of virtuous conduct in every way.  A.iii.36ff.[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Uttara-Vinicchaya[/div][p]A commentary on the  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/vy/vinaya_pitaka,Vinaya Pitaka')"]Vinaya Pitaka[/a], written by  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/b/buddhadatta,Buddhadatta')"]Buddhadatta[/a] as a supplement to his own  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/vy/vinaya_vinicchaya,Vinaya-Vinicchaya')"]Vinaya-Vinicchaya[/a].  [/p][p][/p][p]In manuscripts the two works are usually found together.  [/p][p][/p][p]It was dedicated by the author to one of his pupils  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/sa/sankhapala,Sankhapāla')"]Sankhapāla[/a].  [/p][p][/p][p] [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/va/vaacissara,Vācissara')"]Vācissara[/a] wrote a tīkā on it.  Gv.59, 62. [/p][p][/p][p]The work has been published by the P.T.S.  (1928).[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Uggatasarīra[/div][p]A Mahāsāla brahmin, so called because he was tall in person and eminent in wealth (AA.ii.714).  Having made preparations for a great sacrifice, in which numerous animals were to be slaughtered, he visited the Buddha at Jetavana to consult him as to the efficacy of the sacrifice.  Three times he told the Buddha that he had heard that the laying down (ādhāna) of the fire and the setting up (ussāpana) of the sacrificial post bore great fruit.  Three times the Buddha agreed that it was so, and Uggatasarīra was about to conclude that the Buddha approved of his sacrifice, when Ananda intervened and suggested that the Buddha should be asked to explain his meaning and to give his advice as to the efficacy of the sacrifice.  The Buddha thereupon declared that there were three fires to be cast off: rāga, dosa and moha; and three fires that should be honoured: āhuneyyaggi, gahapataggi and dakkhineyyaggi.  The āhuneyyaggi was represented by the parents; the gahapata, by wife, children, servants and retainers; the dakkhineyya, by holy men and recluses.[/p][p]At the end of the discourse, Uggatasarīra became a convert to the Buddha's faith and set free the animals destined for the sacrifice.  A.iv.41-6.[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Uppala[/div][hr][p]1. Uppala.-A Pacceka Buddha mentioned in the Isigili Sutta.  M.iii.70.[/p][p][/p][p]2. Uppala.-One of the yakkhas who guarded Jotiya's palace.  He had two thousand followers.  DhA.iv.209.[/p][p][/p][p]3. Uppala.-Father of the warrior Ummāda-Phussadeva.  Mhv.xxiii.82.[/p][p][/p][p]4. Uppala (Uppalaka).-A Niraya (S.i.152; Sn.p.126).  Buddhaghosa says (SnA.ii.476f; see also A.v.173), however, that it is not a special hell, but the name of a period of suffering in hell.[/p][p][/p][p]5. Uppala.-One of the treasure-troves that rose up from the earth on the day of the Bodhisatta's birth.  It was three gāvutas in extent.  DA.i.284.[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Utta[/div][p]A thera.  He and his friend Dhanuggahatissa lived in a hut near the Jetavana vihāra.  One night, couriers of Pasenadi, seeking for counsel as to how to win the war against Ajātasattu, overheard a conversation between these two Elders, and acting upon the suggestion contained therein, Pasenadi became victorious (J.ii.403-4).[/p][p]For the story see Danuggahatissa.[/p][hr][p]2. Utta.  See Datta (Mantidatta).[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Ukkatthā[/div][p]A town in Kosala, near the Himālaya.  It has been given, free from all taxes (as brahmadeyya), to Pokkharasātī by the king of Kosala, in recognition of the former's skill.  It was thickly populated and had much grassland, woodland and corn (D.i.87; DA.i.245).  The Icchānangala wood was in the neighbourhood, and when the Buddha was staying in the wood Pokkharasātī first sent his pupil Ambattha and then went himself to visit the Buddha (see the Ambattha Sutta).[/p][p]There was a road which connected Ukkatthā with Setavyā (A.ii.37) and with Vesāli (J.ii.259).  Chatta goes from Setavyā to Ukkatthā to learn under Pokkharasātī (VvA.229).[/p][p][/p][p]It was in the Subhagavana at Ukkatthā that the Mūlapariyāya Sutta (M.i.1ff) was preached and the Mūlapariyāya Jātaka (J.ii.259ff) was related in connection with it.  Ukkatthā was the residence of Anganika-Bhāradvāja (ThagA.339).[/p][p]Buddhaghosa explains (MA.i.9; AA.ii.504) that the city was so called because it was built by the light of torches (ukkā) at night, in order that it might be completed within the auspicious time.[/p][p][/p][p]In the Brahmanimantika Sutta (M.i.326; but see S.i.142; J.iii.359), the Buddha says that it was while he was residing at Subhagavana that be became aware of the erroneous views of Baka-brahma and went to the Brahma-world to teach Baka the truth.  The Divyāvadāna calls the city Ukkatā (p.621).[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Udena Cetiya[/div][p]A shrine of pre-Buddhistic worship, to the east of Vesāli.  [/p][p]It is mentioned with other shrines at Vesāli - [/p][ul][li][p]Gotamaka, [/li][li][p]Sārandada, [/li][li][p]Sattamba, [/li][li][p]Cāpāla and [/li][li][p]Bahuputta - [/li][/ul][p]all of which are described as beautiful spots (D.ii.102; S.v.260; A.iv.309; see also D.iii.9).  [/p][p][/p][p]Rhys Davids conjectures that these were probably trees or barrows (Dial.ii.110, n.1, but see Law: Geography of Early Buddhism.  74ff).  [/p][p][/p][p]The Dhammapada Commentary (iii.246) describes the Udena and the Gotamaka shrines as "rukkha-cetiyas" to which men pay homage in order to have their wishes fulfilled.  [/p][p][/p][p]The Digha Commentary (ii.554; AA.ii.784; UdA.323) says that in the Buddha's time a vihāra had been erected on the spot where this shrine stood and that this vihāra had previously been dedicated to the Yakkha Udena.[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Uttiya[/div][hr][p]1. Uttiya, Uttika.-He was the son of a brahmin of Sāvatthi.  When he came of age, he left the world, seeking "the Deathless," and became a Paribbājaka.  One day, on his travels, he came to the place where the Buddha was preaching and entered the Order, but because of the impurity of his morals he could not win his goal.  Seeing other bhikkhus who had achieved their object, he asked the Buddha for a lesson in brief.  The Buddha gave him a short lesson, which he used for his meditations.  During these meditations he fell ill, but in his anxiety he put forth every effort and became an arahant (Thag.v.30; ThagA.i.89f).[/p][p]In the time of Siddhattha Buddha he was a crocodile in the river Candabhāgā.  One day, seeing the Buddha's desire to cross to the other bank, the crocodile offered him its back to sit on and took him across.[/p][p]Seven times he was king of the devas, and three times ruler of men (Ap.i.79-80).  This Uttiya is evidently identical with the thera of the same name mentioned in the Samyutta Nikāya.  In one sutta (S.v.22) the Buddha explains to him, in answer to his question, the character of the five sensual elements and the necessity for their abandonment.  Elsewhere (S.v.166) he is represented as asking the Buddha for a lesson in brief, which the Buddha gives him.  Dwelling in solitude, he meditates on this and becomes an arahant.[/p][p]Perhaps he is also identical with Uttiya Paribbājaka, who is represented in the Anguttara Nikāya (A.v.193ff) as asking the Buddha various questions on the duration of the world, etc., and as being helped by Ananda to understand the real import of the Buddha's answers.[/p][p][/p][hr][p]2. Uttiya Thera.-He was one of four companions - the others being Godhika, Subāhu and Valliya - who were born at Pāvā as the sons of four Malls-rājās.  They were great friends, and once went together on some embassy to Kapilavatthu.  There they saw the Buddha's Twin Miracle, and, entering the Order, they soon became arahants.  When they went to Rājagaha, Bimbisāra invited them to spend the rainy season there and built for each of them a hut, carelessly omitting, however, to have the huts roofed.  So the theras dwelt in the huts unsheltered.  For a long time there was no rain and the king, wondering thereat, remembered his neglect and had the huts thatched, plastered and painted.  He then held a dedication festival and gave alms to the Order.  The Elders went inside the huts and entered into a meditation of love.  Forthwith the sky darkened in the west and rains fell.[/p][p]In the time of Siddhattha Buddha the four were householders and friends; one of them gave to the Buddha a ladleful of food, another fell prostrate before the Buddha and worshipped him, the third gave him a handful of flowers, while the fourth paid him homage with sumana-flowers.[/p][p]In Kassapa's time, too, they were friends and entered the Order together.  Thag.vv.51-4; ThagA.i.123-6.[/p][p][/p][hr][p]3. Uttiya Thera.-He was a Sākyan of Kapilavatthu.  When the Buddha visited his kinsmen and showed them his power, Uttiya was converted and entered the Order.  One day, while begging in the village, he heard a woman singing and his mind was disturbed.  Checking himself, he entered the vihāra much agitated and spent the siesta, seated, striving with such earnestness that he won arahantship (Thag.v.99; ThagA.i.202-3).[/p][p]In the time of Sumedha Buddha he was a householder and gave to the Buddha a bed, complete with canopy and rug.[/p][p]Twenty kappas ago he was three times king under the name of Suvannābha.[/p][p]He is probably identical with Pallankadāyaka of the Apadāna (Ap.i.175).[/p][p][/p][hr][p]4. Uttiya.-In the Kathāvatthu (i.268) mention is made of a householder Uttiya, together with Yasa-Kulaputta and Setu-mānava, as having attained arahantship while living amid the circumstances of a layman's life.[/p][p][/p][hr][p]5. Uttiya.-One of the theras who accompanied Mahinda on his mission to Ceylon (Mhv.xii.8; Dpv.xii.12; Sp.i.70; Mbv.116).  King Sirimeghavanna had an image of Uttiya made and placed in the image house which he built at the south-eastern corner of his palace.  Cv.xxxvii.87.[/p][p][/p][hr][p]6. Uttiya.-King of Ceylon for ten years (207-197 B.C.) (Dpv.xii.75; Mhv.xx.57).  He was the fourth son of Mutasīva and succeeded Devānampiyatissa.  In the eighth year of his reign died Mahinda (Mhv.xx.33), and in the ninth, Sanghamittā (Mhv.xx.49).  He held great celebrations in honour of these two illustrious dead and built thūpas in various places over their ashes.  The Mahāvamsa Tīkā (p.253) adds that Uttiya built a cetiya at the Somanassamālaka.[/p][p][/p][hr][p]7. Uttiya.-One of the seven warriors of King Vattagāmanī.  He built the Dakkhina-vihāra to the south of Anurādhapura.  Mhv.xxxiii.88.[/p][p][/p][hr][p]8. Uttiya.-See Ayya-Uttiya.[/p][p][/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Upavāna[/div][hr][p]1. Upavāna.-A thera.  He belonged to a very rich brahmin family of Sāvatthi, and having seen the Buddha's majesty at the dedication of Jetavana, he entered the Order and became an arahant with sixfold aññā.  For some time, before Ananda was appointed upatthāka, Upavāna waited on the Buddha.  Once when the Buddha was attacked by cramp, Upavāna, with the help of his lay-friend Devahita, obtained hot water and suitable medicines, with which the ailment was healed; the Buddha, thereupon, expressed his gratitude.  ThagA.i.308ff; this ailment does not seem to be mentioned in Milinda 134f.  where several others are given.  This incident is given at greater length in S.i.174f; see also DhA.iv.232f.[/p][p]When the Buddha lay on his death-bed at Kusināra, Upavāna was by his side fanning him; the Buddha, seeing that he obstructed the vision of the devas who had come to pay their last homage to the Teacher, asked Upavāna to move away (D.ii.138f).[/p][p]Two occasions are mentioned on which Upavāna consulted the Buddha on matters of doctrine, once regarding the arising of suffering (S.ii.41-2) and once on the immediate and practical use of the Dhamma (sanditthikadhamma) (S.iv.41).  There is also recorded a visit of Upavāna to Sāriputta when they were both staying in the Ghositārāma at Kosambī.  Sāriputta asks him about the bojjhangas as being conducive to a happy life and Upavāna explains (S.v.76).  On another occasion Upavāna is the enquirer, and he asks Sāriputta about the "end-maker" (antakara); Sāriputta explains that the "end-maker" is the one who knows and sees things as they really are (A.ii.163).[/p][p]When an unpleasant interview took place between Sāriputta and Lāludāyī (q.v.) and no one was found to support Sāriputta, the matter is reported to the Buddha, who declares that Ananda should have taken Sāriputta's side.  Soon afterwards Ananda seeks Upavāna and tells him that he was too timid to interfere, and if the Buddha referred to the matter again, would Upavāna undertake to answer? In the evening the Buddha engages Upavāna in conversation and asks him to explain the five qualities which make a monk esteemed and loved by his colleagues.  At the end of the discourse the Buddha applauds Upavāna (A.iii.195f).[/p][p]In Padumuttara's time Upavāna had been a poor man.  Seeing people making great offerings at the Buddha's Thūpa, he was much touched, and having washed his upper garment, he hung it as a flag over the Thūpa.  A yakkha named Abhisammataka, who was the guardian of the cetiya, took the flag three times round the cetiya, he himself remaining invisible.[/p][p]A monk whom the man consulted after this miracle foretold that for thirty thousand kappas he would be in the deva-worlds and that he would be deva-king eighty times.  One thousand times he was Cakkavatti.  In his last life his wealth was eighty crores.  When he was Cakkavatti, his banner was held aloft, three leagues in height.  Ap.i.70ff.[/p][hr][p]2. Upavāna.-Son of Anomadassī Buddha.  Bu.viii.19.[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Upasīva[/div][p]One of the disciples of Bāvarī (Sn.v.1007).  The questions he asked the Buddha, when he visited him in the company of his colleagues, are recorded in the Upasīva-mānava-pucchā (Sn.vv.1069-76).  Upasīva joined the Order and became an arahant.  According to the Apadāna (ii.345ff), in the time of Padumuttara he had been an ascetic in a mountain named Anoma, near Himavā.  Once the Buddha visited his hermitage and the ascetic spread a seat for him with grass and flowers and gave him fruit to eat.  He also gave the Buddha a quantity of fragrant aloe-wood.  As a result, he was born in heaven for thirty thousand kappas and was seventy-one times king of the devas.  The Apadāna-account makes no mention of Bāvarī.[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Ukkalā[/div][p]A district (janapada) in the region identified with modern Orissa (CAG., p.733).  The merchants  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/t/tapassu,Tapassu')"]Tapassu[/a] and  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/b/bhallika,Bhalluka')"]Bhalluka[/a] were on the way from Ukkalā, when a certain deva, an erstwhile relative of theirs, advised them to visit the Buddha at Rājāyatanamūla, near  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/u/uruvelaa,Uruvelā')"]Uruvelā[/a], and to offer food to him, which they did (Vin.i.4).  They were on the way to Majjhimadesa (J.i.80).  According to the Theragāthā Commentary (i.48f) there were caravan drivers of a city called Pokkharavatī (probably a town in Ukkalā).  Their destination was evidently  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/r/raajagaha,Rājagaha')"]Rājagaha[/a], for we find them visiting the Buddha there after the first sermon and hearing him preach.[/p][p]The men of Ukkalā, together with those of  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/va/vassa,Vassa')"]Vassa[/a] and  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/b/bhanna,Bhañña')"]Bhañña[/a], are represented as being deniers of cause and effect, deniers of reality (ahetuvādā, akiriyavādā, natthikavādā).  (A.ii.31; S.iii.72; M.iii.78; Kvu.60; AA.ii.497; see also KS.iii.63, and GS.ii.34, n.3).[/p][p]The Mahāvastu (iii.303) places Ukkalā in the Uttarāpatha and mentions Adhisthāna as the place from which Tapussa and Bhalluka hailed.[/p][p]The Mahābhārata (E.g., in Bhīsmapārvan ix.365; Drona iv.122) mentions the Ukkalas several times in lists of tribes (va.  Okkalā).[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Ubhato-vibhanga[/div][p]A collective term, comprehending the Bhikkhu-vibhanga and the Bhikkhunī-vibhanga of the Vinaya Pitaka.  [/p][p]It consists of sixty-four bhānavāras (DA.i.13; Sp.i.15).[/p][p]In the  [a href="http://www.palikanon.com/english/wtb/s_t/saasana,nine-fold division')"]nine-fold division[/a] of the Buddha's teachings - sutta, geyya, etc.  the Ubhato-vibhanga falls into the category of sutta (DA.i.23; Gv.57. 43).  [/p][p]Sometimes the word seems to be used as varia lectio for Ubhato-Vinaya.  E.g., Vin.ii.287; see also Dpv.vii.43.[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Uraga Vagga/Sutta[/div][hr][p][b]1. Uraga Vagga.[/b]-The first chapter of the Sutta Nipāta.  It consists of twelve suttas.  Sn.1ff.[/p][hr][p][b]2. Uraga Vagga.[/b]-The first section of the Peta-Vatthu.  The last story in the section is called Uraga Peta-Vatthu.  Pv., p.11.[/p][hr][p][b]Uraga Sutta.[/b]-The first sutta of the Sutta Nipāta.  It was preached at the Aggālava Cetiya in Ālavī.  The Ālavaka monks cut down trees to build new houses for themselves, and one of them in felling a tree which was the abode of a tree-sprite hurt her child's hand.  Though sorely tempted to kill the monk on the spot, the sprite checked herself and made complaint to the Buddha, who asked her to occupy another tree (SnA.i.3f; the story is also given in Vin.iv.34 and in DhA.iii.229f).  The first stanza of the sutta was preached to the devatā.  The Sutta-Nipāta Commentary (SnA.i.15ff) gives the occasions on which the other stanzas were preached.  Buddhaghosa says (Sp.iv.761) that the devatā mentioned above took up her residence in Jetavana, on a spot indicated to her by the Buddha, and had, therefore, the privilege of listening to the Buddha's sermons at close quarters, even when there were great assemblies of the devas present and less powerful devas, like herself, had generally to yield place to the more powerful.  She could not be dislodged from the place appointed to her by the Buddha.[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Udumbarika-Sīhanāda Sutta[/div][p]Preached at the Udumbarikā-paribbājakārāma.  [/p][p] [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/sa/sandhana,Sandhāna')"]Sandhāna[/a], on his way to see the Buddha, stopped at the paribbājakārāma because it was yet too early for his interview, and started talking to the  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/pa/paribbajaka,Paribbājaka')"]Paribbājaka[/a] [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/n/nigrodha,Nigrodha')"]Nigrodha[/a].  Nigrodha spoke disparagingly of the Buddha's love of solitude.  Seeing the Buddha walking along the banks of the Sumāgadhā, Nigrodha invited him to his hermitage and asked him various questions.  The Buddha turned the discussion on to the merits and demerits of self-mortification and ended up by declaring the purpose of his own teaching.  [/p][p]Though Nigrodha expresses great admiration for the Buddha's exposition, he and his disciples do not become followers of the Buddha (D.iii.36ff).   [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/b/buddhagosa,Buddhaghosa')"]Buddhaghosa[/a] says (DA.iii.844), however, that this sutta will stand them in good stead in the future.[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Upādāna Sutta[/div][hr][p]1. Upādāna Sutta.-Enjoyment brings about craving, grasping, becoming, birth, etc., and, in turn, the whole mass of Ill.[/p][p]It is like a fire with many loads of faggots, constantly supplied with fuel.  S.ii.84f.[/p][p][/p][p]2. Upādāna Sutta.-On grasping and the things that make for it.  S.iii.167.[/p][p][/p][p]3. Upādāna Sutta.-The Buddha teaches the things that make for grasping and the fetters arising there from.  S.iv.89.[/p][p][/p][p]4. Upādāna Sutta.-On grasping and the things that encourage it.  S.iv.108.[/p][p][/p][p]5. Upādāna Sutta.-Jambukhādaka asks Sāriputta what grasping is.  Sāriputta says there are four kinds: grasping after sensuality, opinion, rule and ritual and theory of self.  S.iv.258.[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Ummagga Sutta[/div][p]A certain monk approaches the Buddha and asks various questions: "By what is the world led? By what is it drawn along? Under the sway of what that has arisen, does it go?" The Buddha praises the questioner: "Happy is your approach" (bhaddako te ummaggo) and says that the answer to his question is "thought." "Of what sort is the man widely learned who knows the Dhamma?" "He who understands the meaning and text of the Dhamma and is set on living in accordance with it." Similarly, the man of great wisdom is he who thinks for the profit both of himself and of the whole world.[/p][p]A.ii.177f.  (On the title of the sutta.  and the meaning of the word ummagga see GS.ii.184, n.5)[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Uttamā[/div][hr][p]1. Uttamā.-A therī.  She was born in a banker's family in Sāvatthi and, having heard Patācārā preach, entered the Order.  She could not attain the climax of her insight, till Patācārā, seeing the state of her mind, gave her admonition.  Uttamā thereupon became an arahant (Thig.vv.42-4; ThigA.46ff).  [/p][p]According to the Apadāna (quoted in ThigA.) she joined the Order at the age of seven and attained arahantship within a fortnight.[/p][p]In the time of Vipassī Buddha she had been a slave-girl in a house in Bandhumatī.  At that time King Bandhumā (Vipassī's father) kept fast-days, gave alms and attended sermons, and the people followed his pious example.  The slave-girl joined in these pious acts, and on account of her thoroughness in the observance of fast-days, she was, after death, reborn in Tāvatimsa.  She became the chief queen of the king of the devas sixty-four times, and she was a Cakkavatti's wife in sixty-three births.[/p][p]She is evidently identical with Ekūposathikā of the Apadāna.  Ap.ii.522f.[/p][p][/p][hr][p]2. Uttamā.-A therī.  She was the daughter of an eminent Brahmin of Kosala.  Having heard the Buddha preach during one of his tours, she left the world and soon won arahantship.  She, too, had been a slave girl in Bandhumatī in Vipassī's time.  One day, seeing an arahant seeking alms, she gladly offered him cakes (Thig.vv.45-7; ThigA.49f).[/p][p]She is probably identical with Modakadāyikā of the Apadāna (ii.524f).[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Upasena Sutta[/div][p]Records the incident of the death of Upasena Vangantaputta from a snake-bite.  Summoned by him, Sāriputta looked at him and said that he noticed no change at all in Upasena, either in his body or in his faculties.  Upasena answered that that was because he had long before quelled all lurking tendencies of "I" and "mine." S.iv.40f.[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Upasanta[/div][hr][p]1. Upasanta.-One of the two chief disciples of Atthadassī Buddha (Bu.xv.19; J.i.39).  He was the son of the chaplain of Sucandaka and the friend of Santa.[/p][p]Santa and Upasanta visited the Buddha and for seven days entertained the Buddha and his monks.  The two entered the Order with ninety-eight thousand followers.  BuA.179f.[/p][p][/p][p]2. Upasanta.-A Pacceka Buddha to whom the thera Vajjita, in a previous birth thirty-one kappas ago, gave a campaka-flower.  ThagA.i.336; Ap.i.288.[/p][p][/p][p]3. Upasanta (Upasantaka, Upasaññaka).-The body-servant of Vessabhū Buddha (D.ii.6; Bu.xxii.23; J.i.42).  He was the king of Nārivāhana city and was converted by the Buddha, taking over with him a large following.  BuA.206.[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Usabha [/div][hr][p]1. Usabha Thera.-An arahant.  He was born of a wealthy family in Kosala and entered the Order, when the Buddha accepted Jetavana.  Finishing his novitiate, he dwelt amidst the mountains.  Going out one day from his cave after the rains, he saw the loveliness of the woods and mountains and reflected, "These trees and creepers, though unconscious, yet by the season's fulfilment, have won full growth.  Why should not I, who have obtained suitable season, win growth by good qualities?" Pondering thus, he strove and obtained insight (Thag.v.110; ThagA.i.217f).[/p][p]In the time of Sikhī Buddha, be was a devaputta and offered flowers to the Buddha, which remained as a canopy over the Buddha's head for seven days.  Ten kappas ago be was a king named Jutindhara.  He is evidently to be identified with Mandāravapūjaka of the Apadāna.  Ap.i.178.[/p][p][/p][p]2. Usabha.-He was born of a Sākyan family in Kapilavatthu.  When the Buddha visited his family, Usabha saw his power and wisdom and entered the Order.  But he fulfilled no religious duties, passing the day in society and the night in sleep.  One night he dreamt that he shaved, put on a crimson cloak, and, sitting on a elephant, entered the town for alms.  There, seeing the people gathered together, he dismounted, full of shame.  Filled with anguish at the thought of his own muddleheaded ness, he strove after insight and became an arahant (Thag.197-8; ThagA.i.319f).[/p][p]In the time of Sikhī Buddha he was a householder and gave to the Buddha a kosamba-fruit.  He is evidently identical with Kosambaphaliya of the Apadāna.  Ap.ii.449.[/p][p][/p][p]3. Usabha.-A Pacceka Buddha, mentioned in the Isigili Sutta.  M.iii.70.[/p][p][/p][p]4. Usabha.-A setthi of Kālacampā, father of Sona Kolvisa (AA.i.131; ThagA.i.544).[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Uposathā[/div][p]A pious lay-devotee of Sāketa.  She did many deeds of merit, and was born in Tāvatimsa, her abode being known as the Uposatha-vimāna.  It is said that she was known in Sāketa as Uposatha, because of the life she led.  She expresses to Moggallāna her remorse that she should have desired to be born in Nandana-vana, instead of listening to the Buddha's teaching and putting an end to all birth.  Vv.20f; VvA.115f.[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Ujjaya[/div][hr][p]1. Ujjaya, Ujjāya.-A Pacceka Buddha, mentioned in the list in the Isigili Sutta.  M.iii.70.[/p][p][/p][p]2. Ujjaya.-A thera.  He was the son of a Sotthiya-brahmin of Rājagaha, and became proficient in the three Vedas.  Dissatisfied with the teaching of the Vedas, he went to the Buddha and heard him preach at Veluvana.  Later he entered the Order and retired into the forest, having learnt a subject for meditation.  Soon after he became an arahant.  In a past life he had offered a kanikāra-flower to the Buddha.  Thirty-five kappas ago he was a king named Arunabala (Thag.v.67; ThagA.i.118f).[/p][p]He is probably identical with Kanikārapupphiya of the Apadāna (Ap.i.203).[/p][p][/p][p]3. Ujjaya.-A brahmin.  He once went to the Buddha and asked him if he thought well of sacrifices.  The Buddha replied that he was opposed to sacrifices which involved the slaughter of animals, but sacrifices not necessitating butchery, such as, for instance, a long-established charity, an oblation for the welfare of the family, had his approval (A.ii.42).[/p][p]The same Nikāya (A.iv.285f) records another visit of Ujjaya wherein he tells the Buddha that he wishes to observe a period of retreat (upavāsa), and asks for a teaching which will bring welfare both in this world and in the next.  See below Ujjaya Sutta 2.[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Uragapura[/div][p]The residence of  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/b/buddhadatta,Buddhadatta')"]Buddhadatta[/a], author of the  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/j/jinaalankaara,Jinālankāra')"]Jinālankāra[/a] and several other books.  [p][p]Uragapura was probably in Southern India on the banks of the  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/ka/kaaveri,Kāveri')"]Kāveri[/a].  P.L.C.106f.</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Udāyī [/div][hr][p][b]1. Udāyī Thera.[/b]-Also called Lāludāyī (and Pandita Udāyī), to distinguish him from others.  - He was the son of a brahmin of Kapilavatthu.  He saw the power and majesty of the Buddha when the latter visited his kinsmen and, entering the Order, in due course became an arahant.  When the Buddha preached the Nāgopama Sutta (see A.iii.344f), on the occasion when Seta, King Pasenadi's elephant, was publicly admired, Udāyī was stirred to enthusiasm by thoughts of the Buddha and uttered sixteen verses, extolling the virtues of the Buddha, comparing him to a great and wondrous elephant.  (Thag.vv.689-704; ThagA.ii.7f.; Udāyī's verses are repeated in the Anguttara (iii.346-7) but the Commentary (ii.669) attributes them to Kāludāyī).[/p][p][/p][p]Once when Udāyī was staying at Kāmandā, in Todeyya's mango-grove, he converted a pupil of a brahmin of the Verahaccāni clan and, as a result, was invited by Verahaccāni herself to her house.  It was only on his third visit to Verahaccāni that Udāyī preached to her and she thereupon became a follower of the Faith (S.iv.121-4).  [/p][p][/p][p]The Samyutta Nikāya (iv.166f.; another discussion with Ananda is mentioned in A.iv.426f) also records a conversation between Udāyī and Ananda, when Udāyī asks if it is possible to describe the consciousness, too, as being without the self.  On another occasion Udāyī has a discussion with Pañcakanga on vedanā (M.i.396ff; S.iv.223-4; the Commentary SA.iii.86 and MA.ii.629 here describes Udāyī as "Pandita").  Ananda overhears their conversation and reports it to the Buddha, who says that Udāyī's explanation is true, though not accepted by Pañcakanga.  [/p][p][/p][p]Elsewhere (S.v.86ff) Udāyī is mentioned as asking the Buddha to instruct him on the bojjhangas, and once, at Desaka (Setaka?) in the Sumbha country, he tells the Buddha how he cultivated the bojjhangas and thereby attained to final emancipation (S.v.89).[/p][p][/p][p]He is rebuked by the Buddha for his sarcastic remark to Ananda, that Ananda had failed to benefit by his close association with the Master.  The Buddha assures him that Ananda will, in that very life, become an arahant (A.i.228).[/p][p]Udāyī was evidently a clever and attractive preacher, for he is mentioned as having addressed large crowds, a task demanding great powers, as the Buddha himself says when this news of Udāyī is reported to him (A.iii.184).  [/p][p][/p][p]According to Buddhaghosa (DA.iii.903), it is this same Udāyī (Mahā Udāyī) who, having listened to the Sampasādaniya Sutta, is beside himself with joy at the contemplation of the wonderful qualities as set forth in that Sutta, and marvels that the Buddha does not go about proclaiming them.  Buddhaghosa (MA.i.526) seems to identify him also with the Udāyī to whom the Latukikopama Sutta (M.i.447ff) was preached.[/p][p][/p][hr][p][b]2. Udāyī.[/b]-A thera.  It was once his turn to recite the Pātimokkha before the Sangha, but because he had a crow's voice (kākasaraka), he had to obtain permission to make a special effort so that his recitation might be audible to the others (Vin.i.115).  It is, perhaps, this same monk who is mentioned in the Vinaya as having been guilty of numerous Sanghādisesa offences (Vin.iii.110f, 119f, 127f, 137f, 135ff).  [/p][p][/p][p]He is censured again and again and various penalties are inflicted on him, nevertheless he repeats his offences (Vin.ii.38ff).  In the Nissagyiya (Vin.iii.205f) a story is told of a nun, a former mistress of Udāyī, who conceived a child through touching a garment worn by him.  Once when Uppalavannā asked him to take some meat to the Buddha, he demanded her inner robe as his fees (Vin.iii.208).  He seems to have been very fond of the company of women and they returned his liking.  (See, e.g., Vin.iv.20, 61, 68).  There was evidently a strain of cruelty in him, for we are told of his shooting crows and spitting them with their heads cut off (Vin.iv.124).  He is described as being fat (Vin.iv.171).  He is perhaps to be identified with  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/l/laludayi_th,Lāludāyī')"]Lāludāyī[/a].[/p][p][/p][hr][p][b]3. Udāyī.[/b]-A brahmin.  He visited the Buddha at Sāvatthi and asked if the Buddha ever praised sacrifice.  The Buddha's answer was that he did not commend sacrifices which involved butchery, but praised those which were innocent of any killing (A.ii.43f).[/p][p][/p][hr][p][b]4. Udāyī[/b].-See also under Kāludāyī,  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/l/laludayi_th,Lāludāyī')"]Lāludāyī[/a] and Sakuludāyī.  As they are all, from time to time, referred to as Udāyī it is not always possible to ascertain which is meant.  The Commentary is not an infallible guide.[/p][p][/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Ukkhittapadumiya Thera[/div][p]An arahant.  [/p][p]In the time of Padumuttara Buddha he had been a garland-maker of Hamsavatī.  Once while he was picking lotuses in a pond, the Buddha appeared before him with numerous disciples.  The garland-maker picked a lotus and threw it up into the air, wishing it to remain above the Buddha's head; by the Buddha's power it did thus remain.  As a result, the garland-maker was reborn in Tāvatimsa in a palace named Satapatta.  [/p][p][/p][p]A thousand times he was king of the devas and five hundred times king of men.  Ap.i.275f.[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Ubbarī[/div][hr][p][b]1. Ubbarī.[/b]-A princess.  In the time of Kakusandha she was a hen.  Having heard a monk repeat a formula of meditation, she was born as a royal princess and named Ubbarī.  Seeing a heap of maggots in the privy, she meditated thereon and entered the first jhāna and was born in the Brahma-world.  In the time of Gotama Buddha she was reborn as a sow in Rājagaha, and the Buddha, seeing her, smiled and related her past to Ananda.  Later she was born in the royal household in Suvannabhūmi, then, in succession, in a horse-dealer's house in Suppāraka and in a mariner's household in Kāvīra.  Then she was reborn in a nobleman's house in Anurādhapura, and again in the village of Bokkanta in South Ceylon, as the daughter of a householder named Sumana.  She was called Sumanā, after her father.  When her father moved to the village of Mahāmuni in Dīghavāpi, Lakuntaka Atimbam, prime minister of Dutthagāmani, met her and married her, and she went to live in Mahāpunna.[/p][p]Having recollected her past births from some words uttered by the Elder Anula of Kotipabbata, she joined the Order of Pañcabalaka nuns.  At Tissamahārāma she heard the Mahā Satipatthāna Sutta and became a Sotāpanna.  Later, having heard the Āsīvisopama Sutta in Kallaka-Mahāvihāra, she attained arahantship.  On the day of her death she related her story, first to the nuns and then in the assembly, in the presence of the Elder Mahā Tissa of Mandalārāma.  DhA.iv.46ff.[/p][p][/p][hr][p][b]2. Ubbarī.[/b]-The wife of Cūlanī Brahmadatta, king of Kapila in the Pañcāla kingdom.  She was a daughter of a poor woman in the village, and the king met her while on his wanderings disguised as a tailor, which disguise he assumed in order to find out news of the people for himself.  She was given the name Ubbarī on the day of her marriage, and Cūlanī made her his chief queen.  When the king died, she went to the cemetery day after day, lamenting for her dead husband and refusing to be comforted.  One day the Bodhisatta, who was an ascetic in Himavā, noticed her with his divine eye and appeared before her.  Having heard her story, he pointed out to her that eighty-six thousand kings of Pañcāla, all bearing the name of Cūlanī Brahmadatta, had been burnt in that very spot and that she had been the queen of them all.  Thereupon, Ubbarī abandoned her grief and renounced the world.  She developed thoughts of loving-kindness and in due course was reborn in the Brahma-world (Pv.32; PvA.160-8).[/p][p]She is probably to be identified with the queen of Cūlanī Brahmadatta, king of Pañcāla, mentioned in the Mahā-Ummagga Jātaka (J.vi.473, 475), in which case her original name was Nandā-devī.  According to the scholiast (J.vi.473), Ubbarī is not a proper name but means any women of the court (orodha).[/p][p][/p][hr][p][b]3. Ubbarī.[/b]-Queen Consort of Assaka, king of Potali in the Kāsi kingdom.  She was extremely beautiful and, when she died, the king had her body embalmed and placed in a coffin which was put under his bed.  She, however, was born as a dung-worm because she had been intoxicated by her own beauty.  The story is related in the Assaka Jātaka.  J.ii.155ff.[/p][p][/p][hr][p][b]4. Ubbarī.[/b]-Wife of the Prince Brahmadatta, mentioned in the Dhonasākha Jātaka (J.iii.161).  On his deathbed the king thinks of her longingly and speaks of her as being of swarthy hue.[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Upāli Sutta[/div][hr][p][b]1. Upāli Sutta.[/b]-Records the events that lead to the conversation of  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/u/upaali,Upāli-Gahapati')"]Upāli-Gahapati[/a].  The Buddha is asked, first by  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/d/diighatapassii,Dīgha-Tapassī')"]Dīgha-Tapassī[/a] and then by Upāli, as to which of the three kinds of deeds - of body, speech and mind - are the most criminal.  Those of mind, says the Buddha; those of body, say the followers of Nātaputta.  By various illustrations the Buddha convinces Upāli that his contentions are wrong.  The sutta concludes with a series of verses (the Upāli Gāthā) in which Upāli sings the Buddha's praises.  M.i.371ff.[/p][hr][p][b]2. Upāli Sutta.[/b]-Upāli Thera visits the Buddha and asks him for what purpose the various precepts have been laid down for disciples and why the  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/pa/patimokkha,pātimokkha')"]pātimokkha[/a] has been recited? For ten purposes, says the Buddha, and proceeds to enumerate them.  Similarly, ten reasons are given which justify the suspension of the pātimokkha.  A.v.70f.[/p][hr][p][b]3. Upāli Sutta.[/b]-Upāli (1) visits the Buddha and expresses a desire to retire to the solitude of the forest.  Such a step is not desirable for those who have not attained to tranquillity of mind, says the Buddha, and explains his meaning by various similes.  A full-grown elephant could disport himself in a deep lake according to his fancy, not so a hare or a cat.  The sutta goes on to describe how, as a result of the arising of a Tathāgata in the world, a householder would listen to the Dhamma, renounce the world, give up all evil practices and gradually attain to full development of the four jhānas.  Upāli is advised to live among the monks and not go into the forest.  A.v.201ff.[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Upananda[/div][hr][p][b]1. Upananda.-A thera.[/b] He belonged to the Sākyan clan.  Several incidents connected with him are mentioned in the Vinaya.  Once he promised to spend the rainy season with Pasenadi Kosala, but on his way there he saw two lodgings where robes were plentiful and so kept Vassa in those lodgings instead.  Pasenadi was greatly annoyed and when, in due course, the matter reached the ears of the Buddha, Upananda was rebuked and a set of rules was passed regarding promises made about the rainy season (Vin.i.153).  On another occasion Upananda spent the rainy season at Sāvatthi, but when the time came for the monks to gather together and divide the robes that had been given to them, he went from village to village, taking his share of the robes from everywhere.  The Buddha sent for him and rebuked him in the presence of the Order, but the rebuke had evidently no effect, for we find him again spending the Vassa alone in two residences, with the idea of obtaining many robes.  The Buddha, however, ordered that only one portion should be given to him (Vin.i.300).  His greediness was not confined to robes.  Once he was invited to a meal by an official, a follower of the Ājīvakas.  He went late, and finding no room left for him, made a junior monk get up and give him his seat.  There was a great uproar, but Upananda had his way (Vin.ii.165).  Elsewhere he is accused of having appropriated two lodgings for himself at the same time, one at Sāvatthi and the other somewhere in the country.  He was evidently unpopular among the monks, because on this occasion we find him spoken of as "a maker of strife, quarrelsome, a maker of disputes, given to idle talk, a raiser of legal questions." (Vin.ii.168).  Upananda was fond of money, for we find in the Vinaya (Vin.ii.297) a statement to the effect that "on the occasion of the matter of Upananda the Sākyan, the Buddha distinctly laid down a precept by which gold and silver were forbidden." Upananda had been given his meals regularly by a certain[/p][p]family.  Once a dish of meat was prepared for him, but a little boy in the house started to cry for the meat, and it was given to him.  Upananda insisted that a kahāpana should be paid to him in lieu of the meat (Vin.iii.236f).  Upananda was once asked to preach to those that came to Jetavana.  Among the visitors was a banker, and when the banker expressed the desire to give something to Upananda to show his appreciation of the sermon, Upananda wished to have the robe that the man wore.  The banker was embarrassed, and promised to go home at once and fetch him another robe, even better than the one he had on.  But Upananda was adamant, till, in despair, the man gave him his robe and went away.  Again, when Upananda heard that a certain man wished to offer him a robe, he went to the man and told him what kind of robe he wanted, and said he would accept no other (Vin.iii.215).  A story is also told of a Paribbājaka exchanging his own garment for one belonging to Upananda, which was of rich colour.  Two other Paribbājakas told him that he had lost in the bargain, so he wished to cry off the deal, but Upananda positively refused (Vin.iii.240f).  He did not, however, always come off best[/p][p]in a bargain.  Once he gave a robe to a colleague, on condition that the latter should join him in his tours.  The condition was agreed to, but later, when the recipient monk heard that the Buddha was going on tour, he preferred to join the Buddha's company.  The robe was not returned to Upananda, who had to be reported to the Buddha for the violent language he used to the defaulter (Vin.iii.254f).  Upananda is mentioned as quarrelling with the Chabbaggiya monks (Vin.iv.30) and, at another time, as going his alms-rounds with a colleague with whom he quarrelled when the rounds were over, refusing to give him any of the food obtained.  The unfortunate monk had to starve because it was then too late to go out begging again (Vin.iv.92f).  We are not told whether Upananda deliberately set out to have a quarrel in order that he might keep all the food himself![/p][p]Nor were all Upananda's misdemeanours confined to greed for possessions.  We are told that once a complaint was made to the Buddha that Upananda had gone to the house of an acquaintance and had sat down in the bedroom of the woman of the house, talking to her.  The husband ordered food to be brought to Upananda, and when that was done, asked him to leave.  But the woman wished him to stay and he refused to go away (Vin.iv.94).[/p][p]On two other occasions he is mentioned as visiting the houses of his acquaintances and being found by the husbands, seated alone with their wives (Vin.iv.95-7; see also 121, 127 and 168, for other offences committed by him).[/p][p]With most laymen, however, be was evidently popular.  Mention is made of a meal where the donor kept all the other monks waiting for quite a long while, till Upananda should arrive, after his visits to various households (Vin.iv.98).  And, again, of food being sent to the monastery with express instructions that the other monks should eat only after Upananda had done so (Vin.iv.99).[/p][p]Episodes regarding Upananda's misdeeds are not confined to the Vinaya.  In the Dabbhapuppha Jātaka (J.iii.332ff; see also DhA.iii.139ff) we are told that he was in the habit of preaching contentment to others.  When they, touched by his preaching, cast away their good robes, etc., Upananda collected them for himself.  Once he cheated two brethren of a costly blanket.  When the matter was brought to the Buddha's notice, this Jātaka was related to show how in previous births, too, he had plundered other people's goods.  He had been a jackal called Māyāvī, and had cheated two other jackals of a rohita-fish they had caught.  Again, in the Samudda Jātaka (J.ii.441f), he is described as a great eater and drinker; he would not be satisfied even with cart-loads of provisions.  The Jātaka tells of how he once was born as a water-crow and tried to prevent the fish from drinking the sea-water lest he should not have enough for himself.  Buddhaghosa calls him a lolajātika, held in contempt by his eighty thousand fellow Sākyans who joined the Order (Sp.iii.665).  Elsewhere he is referred to as a well-known example of one who never practised what he preached and, therefore, did not benefit by his cleverness.  E.g., AA.i.92; MA.i.348; Vsm.i.81.[/p][p]Upananda had under him two novices, Kandaka and Mahaka, who seem to have resembled their teacher in being undesirables.  They were found guilty of an unnatural offence, and the Buddha ordered that no one should ordain them (Vin.i.79).  This order seems to have been rescinded later (see Vin.i.83).[/p][hr][p][b]2. Upananda.[/b]-A king of fifty-seven kappas ago; a previous birth of Tindukadāyaka Thera.  Ap.i.201.[/p][hr][p][b]3. Upananda.[/b]-Four Pacceka Buddhas, mentioned in the Isigili Sutta.  M.iii.70.[/p][hr][p][b]4. Upananda.[/b]-Commander-in-chief of the Magadha kingdom.  He was present at the conversation, recorded in the Gopaka-Moggallāna Sutta, between Ananda and Vassakāra.  M.iii.13.[/p][hr][p][b]5. Upananda.[/b] See Nandopananda.[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Upāhana Jātaka (No.  231)[/div][p]Once the Bodhisatta was an elephant-trainer and taught his art to a young man of Kāsi.  The latter wished to take service under the king, but would not accept any fee less than that paid to his teacher.  A contest of skill was arranged to settle the point.  The night before the contest the Bodhisatta taught an elephant to do all things awry, going back when told to go forward, etc.  At the time of the contest the pupil could not match this in any way and was defeated and stoned to death by the onlookers.  The Bodhisatta thereupon declared that a low-bred churl was like an ill-made shoe (upāhana).  The story was told concerning the base ingratitude of Devadatta.  J.ii.221ff.[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Ucchu-vimāna[/div][hr][p]1. Ucchu-vimāna, also called Ucchudāyikā-vimāna.  A girl, who belonged to a pious family in Rājagaha, used to give to holy men half of anything she received.  She was given in marriage to a family of unbelievers.  One day she saw Moggallāna going about for alms, and having invited him to her house she gave him a piece of sugar cane which had been set aside for her mother-in-law, whose approval of the gift she hoped to win.  But when the mother-in-law heard of what had happened in her absence, she flew into a rage and struck the girl with a stool.  The girl died immediately and was born in Tāvatimsa.[/p][p]Later she visited Moggallāna and revealed her identity.  Her palace came to be called Ucchudāyikā-vimāna.  Vv.24f; VvA.124ff.[/p][p][/p][p]2. Ucchu-vimāna.-The story is the same as the above except that the mother in-law struck the girl with a clod of earth.  Vv.44f; VvA.203ff.[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Udakāsanadāyaka Thera[/div][p]An arahant.  Thirty-one kappas ago he had been an ascetic, and at the door of his hermitage he placed a bench for travellers and provided water for them.  [p][p]Fifteen kappas ago he was a king named Abhisāma (Ap.i.218).</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Ummagga-gangā[/div][p]A name given to a part of the river which flows from the east of  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/ay/anotatta,Anotatta')"]Anotatta[/a], before it ultimately divides into the five great rivers,  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/g/gangaa,Gangā')"]Gangā[/a],  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/y/yamunaa,Yamunā')"]Yamunā[/a], etc.  [/p][p]The Ummagga-Gangā is the continuation of the Bahala-Gangā and flows for sixty leagues under the earth, till it reaches the rock named Vijjha.  SnA.ii.439; AA.ii.760; UdA.302.[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Ukkhepakata-Vaccha Thera[/div][p]He was the son of a brahmin of the Vaccha family.  Having heard the Buddha preach, he entered the Order and dwelt in a village settlement in Kosala.  He learnt the doctrine from the various monks who came there from time to time, but it was not until he learnt from Sāriputta that he was able to distinguish between Sutta, Vinaya and Abhidhamma.  He thus became versed in the Three Pitakas even before the First Council (On this see Brethren, p.66. n.1).  He practised meditation and soon attained arahantship (Thag.v.65; ThagA.i.147f).  Later he became a teacher of the doctrine.  According to Dhammapāla (ThagA.i.149), the soubriquet Ukkhepakata was given to him because he was able to teach and recite passages from the three Pitakas "casting them in their proper setting, according as they belonged to each Pitaka." The title was meant to emphasise his eminent repertory of orally-learnt doctrine.[/p][p][/p][p]He had been a householder in the time of the Buddha Siddhattha and had helped a guild who built a hall for the Buddha by giving them a pillar for the building.[/p][p][/p][p]Fifty-five kappas ago he was a king named Yasodhara and twenty-one kappas ago another king named Udena.  His seven-storied palaces were all built on one pillar.  He is probably to be identified with Ekatthambhika Thera of the Apadāna (i.56-7).[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Upaka[/div][hr][p][b]1. Upaka[/b][/p][p]An  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/aa/aajiivakaa,Ājivaka')"]Ājivaka[/a] whom the Buddha met on his way between  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/g/gayaa,Gayā')"]Gayā[/a] and the Bodhi Tree, after he set out from  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/i_/isipatana,Isipatana')"]Isipatana[/a] for the preaching of the First Sermon.  Upaka questioned the Buddha on his attainments, and when the Buddha told him what he had accomplished he asked the Buddha if he were "Anantajina." When the Buddha acknowledged it, Upaka shook his bead saying, "It may be so, friend," and went along by another road (J.i.81; Vin.i.8; M.i.170-1; DhA.iv.71-2).  It is said (DA.ii.471) that the Buddha walked all the way from the Bodhi Tree to Isipatana - instead of flying through the air, as is the custom of Buddhas - because he wished to meet Upaka.[/p][p]After this meeting Upaka went to the  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/va/vankahaara,Vankahāra')"]Vankahāra[/a] country and there, having fallen desperately in love with  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/c/caapaa_thi,Cāpā')"]Cāpā[/a], the daughter of a huntsman who looked after him, starved for seven days and in the end persuaded the huntsman to give her to him in marriage.  For a living, Upaka hawked about the flesh brought by the huntsman.  In due course Cāpā bore him a son, Subhadda.  When the baby cried, Cāpā sang to him saying, "Upaka's son, ascetic's son, game-dealer's boy, don't cry," thus mocking her husband.  In exasperation he told her of his friend Anantajina, but she did not stop teasing him.  One day, in spite of her attempts to keep him, he left her and went to the Buddha at  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/sa/saavatthi,Sāvatthi')"]Sāvatthi[/a].  The Buddha, seeing him coming, gave orders that anyone asking for Anantajina should be brought to him.  Having learnt from Upaka his story, the Buddha had him admitted to the Order.  As a result of his meditation, Upaka became an anāgāmī and was reborn in the  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/ay/avihaa,Avihā')"]Avihā[/a] heaven (ThigA.220ff; MA.i.388f.  Upaka's story is also given in SnA.i.258ff, with several variations in detail).  The Samyutta Nikāya (i.35, 60) records a visit paid to the Buddha by Upaka and six other beings born in Avihā.  According to the Majjhima Commentary (i.389), Upaka became an arahant as soon as he was born in Avihā.[/p][p]In the Therīgāthā he is also called Kāla (v.309. This may have been a term of affection used because of his dark colour) and his birth-place is given as Nāla, a village near the Bodhi Tree, where he is said to have been living with his wife at the time he left her (ThigA.225).[/p][p]Later, Cāpā, too, left the world and became an arahant Therī.  [/p][p]The Divyāvadana (p.393) calls Upaka Upagana.[/p][p]The enumeration of the Buddha's virtues which was made to Upaka is not regarded as a real dhammadesanā because it took place before the preaching of the first sermon.  It produced only a vāsanā-bhāgiya result, not sekha- or ribaddha-bhāgiya (UdA.54).[/p][p]The words of the Buddha's speech to Upaka are often quoted (E.g., Kvu.289).[/p][hr][p][b] [a name="2"]2[/a].  Upaka Mandikāputta.[/b]-He once visited the Buddha at  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/g/gijjhakuuta,Gijjhakūta')"]Gijjhakūta[/a] and stated before him his view that whoever starts abusive talk of another, without being able to make good his case, is blameworthy.  The Buddha agrees and says that Upaka himself has been guilty of this offence.  The Commentary (AA.ii.554) explains that Upaka was a supporter of  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/d/devadatta,Devadatta')"]Devadatta[/a].  Upaka protests against being caught in a big noose of words, like a fish caught as soon as he pops up his head.  The Buddha explains that it is necessary for him to teach with endless variations of words and similes.  Upaka is pleased with the Buddha's talk and reports the conversation to  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/am/ajatasattu,Ajātasattu')"]Ajātasattu[/a].  The king shows his anger at the man's presumption in having remonstrated with the Buddha (A.ii.181f), and the Commentary adds that he had him seized by the neck and cast out.[/p][p]Buddhaghosa says (AA.ii.554-5) that Upaka went to visit the Buddha in order to find out whether the Buddha would blame him for being a supporter of Devadatta.  According to others, he came to abuse the Buddha because he had heard that the Buddha had consigned Devadatta to hell.  He was apparently of low caste, and  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/am/ajatasattu,Ajātasattu')"]Ajātasattu[/a] addresses him as "salt-worker's boy" (lonakārakadāraka) (A.ii.182).[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Ulunkasaddaka[/div][p]The nickname of a young novice who lived with  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/maha/maha_kassapa_th,Mahākassapa')"]Mahākassapa[/a] and who later burnt down the Elder's hut in  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/r/raajagaha,Rājagaha')"]Rājagaha[/a].  [p][p]His story is related in the [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/ku/kutiduusaka_jat_321,Kutidūsaka Jātaka')"]Kutidūsaka Jātaka[/a].  (J.iii.71ff).</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Uppatika Sutta[/div][p]On the five controlling faculties (indriyāni) - of discomfort, of unhappiness, of ease, of happiness and of indifference - and on how they are conditioned and how they cease to be (S.v.213f).  According to the Commentary (SA.iii.192), the title of this sutta should be Uppatipātika Sutta (the sutta which deals with reference to what has gone before).[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Uraga Jātaka (No.  154).[/div][hr][p]1. Uraga Jātaka (No.  154).-King Brahmadatta of Benares once held a festival to which came the inhabitants of many worlds.  A Nāga in the crowd, not noticing that the person beside him was a Garuda, laid a hand on his shoulder; discovering his mistake, he was frightened to death and ran away, pursued by the Garuda.  The Nāga, coming to a river, where an ascetic, who was the Bodhisatta, was bathing, took refuge in the ascetic's bark-garment.  The Garuda, though able to see the Nāga, would not attack him out of respect for the ascetic.  The latter took both of them to his hermitage and made them friendly towards each other by preaching the blessings of loving-kindness.[/p][p]The story was related in reference to two soldiers who were in the habit of quarrelling whenever they met.  Not even the king could reconcile them.  The Buddha visited them at their homes and, having made them both sotāpannas, took them to see each other.  Thenceforth they were great friends, and people marvelled at the Buddha's power (J.ii.12-14).  The Nakula Jātaka was also preached in this connection.[/p][p][/p][hr][p]2. Uraga Jātaka (No.  354).-The Bodhisatta was once a brahmin in Benares.  His household consisted of himself, his wife, a son, a daughter, a daughter-in-law and a female slave.  They lived happily together, and on the Bodhisatta's advice kept their thoughts constantly fixed on the inevitableness of death.  One day, while burning some rubbish in the field, the son was bitten by a snake and died.  The father laid his body under a tree, and having sent word to his house that all the others should come with perfumes and flowers, when bringing his meal, be went on with his work.  After the meal they made a funeral pyre and burnt the body, but not one of them wept a single tear.  By virtue of their piety, Sakka's throne was heated and he appeared to them in disguise.  He questioned them separately as to whether their lack of any show of grief for the dead meant that they did not love him.  Being convinced that their composure was due to their practice of the thought of death, he revealed his identity, and filled their house with the seven kinds of treasures.  The story was related to a landowner of Sāvatthi who, when his son died, gave himself up to despair.  The Buddha visited him and consoled him (J.iii.162ff).[/p][p]This story is referred to in the Dhammapada Commentary DhA.iii.277.[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Ubbirī Therī[/div][p]She was born in the family of a very rich burgess of Sāvatthi and was married to the king of Kosala (probably Pasenadi).  After a few years a daughter was born to her, whom she named Jivā (v.l.  Jīvantī).  The king was so pleased with the child that he had Ubbirī anointed as queen.  But the girl died soon afterwards, and Ubbirī, distracted, went daily to the charnel-field.  One day, as she sat lamenting on the bank of the Aciravatī, the Buddha appeared before her in a ray of glory.  Having listened to her story, the Master pointed out to her that in that same burial-ground, eighty-four thousand of her daughters, all named Jīvā, had been burnt.  Pondering on the Master's words, she developed insight and became an arahant.[/p][p]When she was a young girl in Hamsavatī in the time of Padumuttara Buddha, she was one day left alone in the house.  Seeing an arahant begging for alms, she invited him in and gave him food.  As a result she was born in Tāvatimsa.  Eighty times she reigned as queen in heaven and seventy times as queen among men (Thig.vv.51-2; ThigA.53ff).[/p][p]No mention is made in the Therīgāthā Commentary of her having joined the Order, but the Apadāna (ii.525f) states that she did so.[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Upakārī[/div][hr][p]1. Upakārī.-A city of the Pañcālas (J.vi.448, 450, 458, 459).  Here was the entrance to the tunnel through which King Vedeha escaped to Mithilā, as related in the Mahā Ummagga Jātaka (q.v.).[/p][p][/p][p]2. Upakārī.-A city where Sumedha Buddha preached to a large concourse of people.  BuA.165.[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Upacālā[/div][hr][p]1. Upacālā.-Sister of Sāriputta (his other sisters being Cālā, Sisūpacālā) and mother of Upacāla.  When Sāriputta left the world to join the Order of monks, his three sisters followed his example and became nuns.  It is said that when Upacālā was taking her siesta in Andhavana, Māra tried to arouse in her sensual desires, but she vanquished him and became an arahant.  Her conversation with Māra is recorded in the Therīgāthā vv.189-95; ThigA.165f.  The Samyutta (i.133f) mentions the temptation of all three sisters by Māra and their conquest of him.  But in this account, Upacālā's verses are put into Cālā's mouth, Sisūpacālā's are ascribed to Upacālā and Cālā's to Sisūpacālā.[/p][p][/p][p]2. Upacālā.-The chief of the women disciples of Phussa Buddha.[/p][p]See also Upasālā.  (J.i.41; Bu.xix.20).[/p][p][/p][p]3. Upacālā.-Chief of the women supporters of Sumana Buddha.  Bu.v.28.[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Uttarakuru[/div][p]A country often mentioned in the Nikāyas and in later literature as a mythical region.  A detailed description of it is given in the  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/aa/aataanaatiya_s,Ātānātiya Sutta')"]Ātānātiya Sutta[/a].  (D.iii.199ff; here Uttarakuru is spoken of as a city, pura; see also Uttarakuru in Hopkins: Epic Mythology, especially p.186).  The men who live there own no property nor have they wives of their own; they do not have to work for their living.  The corn ripens by itself and sweet-scented rice is found boiling on hot oven-stoves.  The inhabitants go about riding on cows, on men and women, on maids and youths.  Their king rides on an elephant, on a horse, on celestial cars and in state palanquins.  Their cities are built in the air, and among those mentioned are Ātānātā, Kusinātā, Nātapuriyā, Parakusinātā, Kapīvanta, Janogha, Navanavatiya, Ambara-Ambaravatiya and  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/aa/aalakamandaa,Ālakamandā')"]Ālakamandā[/a], the last being the chief city.[/p][p]The king of Uttarakuru is  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/ku/kuvera,Kuvera')"]Kuvera[/a], also called Vessavana, because the name of his citadel (? rājadhāni) is Visāna.  His proclamations are made known by Tatolā, Tattalā, Tatotalā, Ojasi, Tejasi, Tetojasi, Sūra, Rāja, Arittha and Nemi.  Mention is also made of a lake named Dharanī and a hall named Bhagalavati where the Yakkhas, as the inhabitants of Uttarakuru are called, hold their assemblies.[/p][p]The country is always spoken of as being to the north of Jambudīpa.  It is eight thousand leagues in extent and is surrounded by the sea (DA.ii.623; BuA.113).  Sometimes it is spoken of (E.g., A.i.227; v.59; SnA.ii.443) as one of the four Mahādīpā - the others being  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/ay/aparagoyaana,Aparagoyāna')"]Aparagoyāna[/a],  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/pu/pubbavideha,Pubbavideha')"]Pubbavideha[/a] and  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/j/jambudiipa,Jambudīpa')"]Jambudīpa[/a]- each being surrounded by five hundred minor islands.  These four make up a  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/c/cakkavaala,Cakkavāla')"]Cakkavāla[/a], with Mount Meru in their midst, a flat-world system.  A cakkavattī's rule extends over all these four continents (D.ii.173; DA.ii.623) and his chief queen comes either from the race of King Madda or from Uttarakuru; in the latter case she appears before him of her own accord, urged on by her good fortune (DA.ii.626; KhA.173).[/p][p]The trees in Uttarakuru bear perpetual fruit and foliage, and it also possesses a Kapparukkha which lasts for a whole kappa (A.i.264; MA.ii.948).  There are no houses in Uttarakuru, the inhabitants sleep on the earth and are called, therefore, bhūmisayā (ThagA.ii.187-8).[/p][p]The men of Uttarakuru surpass even the gods of  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/t/taavatimsa,Tāvatimsa')"]Tāvatimsa[/a] in four things: [/p][ul][li]they have no greed (amamā) (the people of Uttarakuru are acchandikā, VibhA.461), [/li][li]no private property (apariggahā), [/li][li]they have a definite term of life (niyatāyukā) (one thousand years, after which they are born in heaven, says  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/b/buddhagosa,Buddhaghosa')"]Buddhaghosa[/a], AA.ii.806) [/li][li]and they possess great elegance (visesabhuno).  [/li][/ul][p]They are, however, inferior to the men of Jambudīpa in courage, mindfulness and in the religious life (A.iv.396; Kvu.99).[/p][p]Several instances are given of the  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/b/buddha,Buddha')"]Buddha[/a] having gone to Uttarakuru for alms.  Having obtained his food there, he would go to the  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/ay/anotatta,Anotatta')"]Anotatta[/a] lake, bathe in its waters and, after the meal, spend the afternoon on its banks (See, e.g., Vin.i.27-8; DhsA.16; DhA.iii.222).  The power of going to Uttarakuru for alms is not restricted to the Buddha;  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/pa/pacceka_buddha,Pacceka Buddhas')"]Pacceka Buddhas[/a] and various ascetics are mentioned as having visited Uttarakuru on their begging rounds (See, e.g., J.v.316; vi.100; MA.i.340; SnA.ii.420).  It is considered a mark of great iddhi-power to be able to do this (E.g., Rohita, SA.i.93; also Mil.84).[/p][p]Jotika's wife was a woman of Uttarakuru; she was brought to  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/j/jotika,Jotika')"]Jotika[/a] by the gods.  She brought with her a single pint pot of rice and three crystals.  The rice-pot was never exhausted; whenever a meal was desired, the rice was put in a boiler and the boiler set over the crystals; the heat of the crystals went out as soon as the rice was cooked.  The same thing happened with curries (DhA.iv.209ff).  Food never ran short in Uttarakuru; once when there was a famine in  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/vy/veranjaa,Verañjā')"]Verañjā[/a] and the  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/b/buddha,Buddha')"]Buddha[/a] and his monks were finding it difficult to get alms, we find  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/maha/maha_moggallana_th,Moggallāna')"]Moggallāna[/a] suggesting that they should go to Uttarakuru for alms (Vin.iii.7).  The clothes worn by the inhabitants resembled divine robes (See, e.g., PvA.76).[/p][p]It was natural for the men of Uttarakuru not to transgress virtue, they had pakati-sīla (Vsm.i.15).[/p][p]Uttarakuru is probably identical with the Kuru country mentioned in the Rg-Veda (See Vedic Index).[/p][hr][p][b]2. Uttuakuru.[/b]-A garden laid out by Parakkamabāhu I.  (Cv.lxxix.11).[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Uruvelamandala[/div][p]A district in Rohana, in South Ceylon, where the ministers Bhūta, Rakkha and Kitti obtained a decisive victory over their enemies.  This battle enabled them to get possession of the Buddha's Bowl and the Tooth Relic (Cv.lxxiv.125-6).  Geiger thinks that the place was near the modern Monarāgala (Cv.Trs.ii.33, n.1).[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Utthāna Sutta[/div][p]The  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/b/buddha,Buddha')"]Buddha[/a] was once staying in the upper storey of the  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/me_mu/migaramatupasada,Migāramātupāsāda')"]Migāramātupāsāda[/a] when he heard the new entrants to the Order, in the cells below, making a great uproar, talking about the food they had eaten, and other such worldly topics.  The Buddha desired  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/maha/maha_moggallana_th,Moggallāna')"]Moggallāna[/a] to come and, when he appeared, the Buddha asked him to frighten the monks by a display of iddhi-power.[/p][p]By his psychic power Moggallāna caused the whole building to rock to and fro like a ship, and when the monks, in terror, sought the Buddha's protection, he explained to them that Moggallāna gave them the fright as a lesson to them to lead active and energetic lives, for death lays hold of the slothful.[/p][p]The monks having listened to the Buddha's sermon, concentrated their minds on it, and soon after became arahants.  Sn.vv.331-4; SnA.i.336f; cf.  S.v.269ff.[/p][p]See also  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/pa/pasadakampana,Pāsādakampana Sutta')"]Pāsādakampana Sutta[/a].[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Udakūpama Sutta[/div][p]There are seven kinds of people in the world who are like objects that fall into wells: Some having sunk into the water remain there; others continue sinking and rising; some having risen once will not sink again; others having risen will look round, etc.  Similarly, some having fallen into sin never escape there from, others are prone to weakness but often check themselves, etc.  A.iv.11-13.[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Ummagga Jātaka[/div][hr][p]1. Ummagga Jātaka.-See Mahā-Ummagga Jātaka.[/p][p][/p][p]2. Ummagga Jātaka.-The Samantapāsādikā (iv.742) mentions a work called the Gūlha-Ummagga in a list of heretical works which pass off as the word of the Buddha, but which are the teachings of unbelievers.[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Upaddhadussadāyaka Thera[/div][p]An arahant.  In the time of Padumuttara Buddha, he had been a labourer, and seeing a monk, named Sujāta, looking for rags for a robe, he gave him half the garment he wore.  As a result he became king of the gods thirty-three times and king of men seventy-seven times.  Ap.ii.436f.[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Udumbara-devi[/div][p]Wife of Pinguttara.  She was the daughter of a teacher in Takkasilā and was given to Pinguttara because he was the eldest pupil.  But he was unhappy with her, and on the way to his home, when she climbed up a fig (udumbara) tree to pluck fruits for herself, he put thorns round the tree and ran away, leaving her.  The king, coming along, saw her and married her.  She was called Udumbara-devi because of the circumstances in which she was found.  When the king suspected her of infidelity to him, Mahosadha saved her from ignominy, and she became thereafter his best friend and helped him in all his doings, treating him, with the king's permission, as her younger brother.  When the king planned to kill Mahosadha, Udumbara-devi warned him in time and enabled him to evade the treachery of his enemies at court (J.vi.348, 352, 355, 363, 368, 384).[/p][p]In the present age she was Ditthamangalikā (J.vi.478).  [/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Unnābha[/div][p]A brahmin.  He once visited the Buddha at Sāvatthi and asked him whether the five sense-faculties (indriyāni), which were of different scope and range, had any common ground of resort (pati-sarana).  The Buddha replies that the mind is their common resort and, in answer to further questions, explains that there is nothing beyond Nibbāna; that the holy life has Nibbāna for its ending.[/p][p]When the brahmin, greatly pleased with the Buddha's teaching, goes away, the Buddha tells the monks that Unnābha has become an anāgāmī and would, therefore, after death, no longer return to this world (S.v.217f).[/p][p]The same Nikāya (S.v.272f) records a visit of Unnābha to Ananda at Kosambī.  He asks Ananda what is the aim of holy life and, on being told that it is the abandoning of desire by means of jhāna, suggests that it would be a task without end.  But Ananda, by means of an illustration, explains how the task does come to an end, and Unnābha expresses great satisfaction with the answer.  Perhaps this refers to another brahmin of the same name.[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Ulāra-vimāna[/div][p]The daughter of a family in Rājagaha, which waited upon Mahā Moggallāna; was very generous and always gave away in alms the half of anything which she possessed.  She was given in marriage to the son of a family of unbelievers.  One day, seeing Moggallāna begging for alms, she invited him and gave him some cakes which had been put away by her mother-in-law.  When the latter heard of it she was greatly enraged, and struck the girl with a pestle.[/p][p]The girl died and was born in Tāvatimsa, her palace being called the Ulāravimāna.  Later, Moggallāna visited her there (Vv.p.24; VvA.120).[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Ubhatobhattha Jātaka (No.  139)[/div][p]Once in a village of line-fishermen one of the men took his tackle and went with his little son to fish.  A snag caught hold of his line, but the man, thinking it was a big fish, sent his son home to ask his mother to pick a quarrel with the neighbours in order to keep them occupied lest they should claim a share of his catch.  When the boy had gone, the fisherman went into the water to drag the fish, but he struck against the snag and was blinded in both eyes.  Moreover a robber stole his clothes from the bank and his wife was taken before the village chief and fined and beaten for quarrelling.  The Bodhisatta who was a Tree-deva saw all this happen and drew a moral from it.  The story was told in reference to Devadatta, who is identified with the fisherman, all his enterprises having come to grief.  J.i.482-4.[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Upasālha Jātaka (No.  166)[/div][p]Preached to Upasālha.  The story of the past is that of a brahmin Upasālhaka (identified with Upasālha).  He instructed his son that after death he should be burnt in a cemetery unpolluted by the presence of outcasts.  While descending Gijjhakūta, having ascended the mountain in order to find such a spot, they met the Bodhisatta, who was a holy ascetic, possessed of various attainments and mystic powers.  When the Bodhisatta had heard their story, he revealed to them that on that very same spot Upasālha had been burnt fourteen thousand times, and preached to them the way of deathlessness (J.ii.54ff).[/p][p]The Upasālhaka Jātaka was preached by the Buddha to the novice Vanavāsī-Tissa when the Buddha visited him in his forest solitude.  DhA.ii.99.[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Ujjenī[/div][hr][p][b]1. Ujjenī.[/b]-The capital of [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/ay/avanti,Avanti')"]Avanti[/a].  In the Buddha's time,  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/c/cannda_ppajjota,Canda-Pajjota')"]Canda-Pajjota[/a] (Vin.i.276; DhA.i.192) was king of Ujjenī and there was friendly intercourse between that city and  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/ma/magadha,Magadha')"]Magadha[/a], whose king was Seniya [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/b/bimbisara,Bimbisāra')"]Bimbisāra[/a].  After Bimbisāra's death, however, Pajjota seems to have contemplated a war against  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/am/ajatasattu,Ajātasathu')"]Ajātasathu[/a].  See M.iii.7.[/p][p]There was an old trade-route from Ujjenī to Benares and the merchants of the two cities showed healthy rivalry not only in trade, but also in matters of culture.  See, e.g., J.ii.248ff., where the merchants of Benares compare their musician  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/g/guttila,Guttila')"]Guttila[/a] with  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/me_mu/musila,Mūsila')"]Mūsila[/a], the chief fiddler of Ujjenī.[/p][p]It was while going with a caravan to Ujjenī, that  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/s/sona,Sona Kutikanna')"]Sona Kutikanna[/a] (4) met the Peta, whose words made him decide to renounce household life (UdA.307f).[/p][p]The road taken by  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/b/bavari,Bāvarī')"]Bāvarī's[/a] disciples ran through  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/u/ujjenii,Ujjenī')"]Ujjenī[/a] (Sn.v.1011).[/p][p]Ujjenī was also the birthplace of  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/maha/maha_kaccaana,Mahā Kaccāna')"]Mahā Kaccāna[/a] (ThagA.i.483), of  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/i_/isidaasii_thi,Isidāsī')"]Isidāsī[/a] (Thig.v.405), of  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/am/abhaya,Abhaya')"]Abhaya[/a] (ThagA.41) and of the courtesan  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/pa/padumavati,Padumavatī')"]Padumavatī[/a], mother of  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/am/abhayaa,Abhayā')"]Abhayā[/a] (ThigA.39).[/p][p]Before succeeding to his father's throne at  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/pa/paataliputta_gama,Pātaliputta')"]Pātaliputta[/a],  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/ay/asoka,Asoka')"]Asoka[/a] reigned for several years as Viceroy at Ujjenī, and it was during this period that  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/ma/mahinda,Mahinda')"]Mahinda[/a] and [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/sa/sanghamitta_theri,Sanghamittā')"]Sanghamittā[/a] were born (Mhv.xiii.10ff; Mbv.99; Sp.i.70).[/p][p]Mahinda spent six months in Dakkhinagiri Vihāra in Ujjenī, prior to his visit to Ceylon (Mhv.xiii.5).[/p][p]From the same vihāra forty thousand monks were present, under the leadership of Mahā Sangharakkhita, at the foundation of the Mahā Thūpa in Anurādhapura (Mhv.xxix.35).[/p][p]The Jātakas speak of Ujjenī as having been the capital of Avanti from very ancient times.  E.g., in J.iv.390, where Avanti Mahārāja rules in Ujjenī as capital of Avanti.  But in the Mahāgovinda Sutta (D.ii.235), Māhissatī is mentioned as the capital of Avanti.  Perhaps Māhissatī lost its importance later and gave place to Ujjenī, for we find Māhissatī mentioned just before Ujjenī among the places passed by Bāvarī's pupils on their way to Sāvatthi (Sn.v.1011).[/p][p]Ujjenī is identical with the Greek Ozene, about 77° E.  and 23° N.  (Bud.  India, p.40; see also CAGI, 560, and Beal ii.270 for  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/h/hiuen_tsang,Hiouen Thsang')"]Hiouen Thsang's[/a] description of it).[/p][hr][p][b]2. Ujjenī.[/b]-A city in Ceylon, founded by Vijaya's minister Accutagāmī (Dpv.ix.36; Mhv.vii.45).[/p][hr][p][b]3. Ujjenī.[/b]-A township (nigama), the residence of the banker's daughter Rucinandā, who gave a meal of milk-rice to Padumuttara Buddha just before his Enlightenment (BuA.158).[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Ucchu[/div][p]The name given to one of the stories of the Petavatthu.  The peta referred to had been a resident near Veluvana.  Once he was going along the road eating a sugar cane and carrying a bundle of sugar canes.  Behind him came another man of good conduct, with a child.  The child, seeing the sugar cane, begged for some of it with great lamentations.  The good man wishing to console the child, walked up to the sugar cane-eater and tried to make friends.  His efforts were, however, unsuccessful, and when he begged for a piece of sugar cane for the child, the man sulkily threw him a bit from the end of the sugar cane.  This man, after his death, was born as a peta.  Around him was a forest of sugar canes, but whenever he attempted to eat any of them he got badly bruised and wounded.  One day Moggallāna saw him, and having discovered his antecedents told him about his past profitless life.  He made the peta get for him a piece of sugar cane, which he offered to the Buddha and the monks.  As a result of this, the peta was reborn in Tāvatimsa.  Pv., pp.61f; PvA.257ff.[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Ukkācelā[/div][p]A village in the  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/va/vajjii,Vajji')"]Vajji[/a] country, on the banks of the Ganges, on the road from  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/r/raajagaha,Rājagaha')"]Rājagaha[/a] to [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/vy/vesaali,Vesāli')"]Vesāli[/a] and near the latter (UdA.322).  [/p][p]Once while  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/sa/saariputta,Sāriputta')"]Sāriputta[/a] was staying there, the Paribbājaka [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/sa/samandaka,Sāmandaka')"]Sāmandaka[/a] visited him and talked to him about Nibbāna (S.iv.261-2).  Some time later, after the death of Sāriputta and  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/maha/maha_moggallana_th,Moggallāna')"]Moggallāna[/a] within a fortnight of each other, the Buddha came to Ukkacelā on his way to Vesāli and at a gathering of the monks uttered high praise of the two chief disciples and spoke of the loss the Order had sustained by their death (S.v.163f).[/p][p]The  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/c/cuula_gopaalaka_s,Cūlagopālaka Sutta')"]Cūlagopālaka Sutta[/a] was also preached at Ukkacelā (M.i.225).  [/p][p] [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/b/buddhagosa,Buddhaghosa')"]Buddhaghosa[/a] says (MA.i.447) that when the city was being built, on the day its site was marked out, fish came ashore at night from the river, and men, noticing them, made torches (ukkā) out of rags (celā), dipped them in oil, and by their light caught the fish.  On account of this incident the city was called Ukkācelā (v.l.  Ukkacelā, Ukkāvelā).[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Uruvela Sutta[/div][hr][p]1. Uruvela Sutta.-Preached at Jetavana.  The Buddha tells the monks how, when he was at Uruvelā, under the Ajapāla tree, he realised that there was no one in the world worthy to be his teacher.  So he decided to obey and serve the Dhamma.  Sahampatī appeared and told him that such had been the custom of previous Buddhas also (A.ii.20f).[/p][p][/p][p]2. Uruvela Sutta.-The Buddha tells the monks how a number of brahmins bad visited him at Uruvelā and asked him if it were true that he did not reverence old men? He taught them how it was not old age which deserved reverence, but the qualities which men possessed, and he set forth those qualities (A.ii.22f).[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Ubbhataka[/div][p]A mote-hall built by the  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/ma/mallaa,Mallas')"]Mallas[/a] of  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/pa/pava,Pāvā')"]Pāvā[/a].  When it was finished they invited the  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/b/buddha,Buddha')"]Buddha[/a] to be its first occupant.  The Buddha went with the monks and spent the night in the hall.  It was on this occasion that  [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/sa/saariputta,Sāriputta')"]Sāriputta[/a] recited the [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/sa/sangiti_sutta,Sangīti Sutta')"]Sangīti Sutta[/a] (D.iii.207ff).[/p][p] [a href="javascript:void(0)" onclick="DPPNXML('dppn/b/buddhagosa,Buddhaghosa')"]Buddhaghosa[/a] says (DA.iii.971) that the hall was so-called ("Thrown-aloft-er") because of its great height.[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Udapānadūsaka Jātaka (No.  271)[/div][p]In times gone by, the Bodhisatta, having embraced the religious life, dwelt with a body of followers at Isipatana.  A jackal was in the habit of fouling the well from which the ascetics obtained their water.  One day the ascetics caught the jackal and led him before the Bodhisatta.  When questioned, the jackal said that he merely obeyed the "law" of his race, which was to foul the place where they had drunk.  The Bodhisatta warned him not to repeat the offence.[/p][p][/p][p]The story was related concerning the fouling of the water at Isipatana by a jackal.  When this fouling was reported to the Buddha, he said it was caused by the jackal which had been guilty of the same offence in the Jātaka-story.  J.ii.354ff.[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Upaddha Sutta[/div][p]Preached at the Sākyan township of Sakkara.  Ananda mentions to the Buddha his view that half the holy life consists in friendship with the good.  The Buddha says that it is not the half but the whole of the holy life, and proceeds to explain (S.v.2).  In the Kosala Samyutta (S.i.87) we find the Buddha relating this incident to Pasenadi.[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Udumbara Jātaka (No.  298)[/div][p]The story of two monkeys.  One, small and red-faced, lived in a rock cave.  During heavy rains, the other, a large and black-faced monkey, saw him, and wishing to have the shelter for himself, sent him away, on the pretext that outside in the forest there was plenty of food to be had.  The small monkey was taken in by the trick, and when he came back he found the other monkey, with his family, installed in the cave.[/p][p][/p][p]The story was told in reference to a monk who lived comfortably in a village hermitage and was ousted from there by another monk whom he had welcomed as a guest.  J.ii.444-6.[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Usīnara[/div][p]King of Benares in the time of Kassapa Buddha.  His story is related in the Mahā-Kanha Jātaka (J.iv.181ff).  He is mentioned in a list of kings who, although they gave great gifts, could not get beyond the domain of sense (J.vi.99).  He is, however, elsewhere (J.vi.251) mentioned as having been born in Sakka's heaven as a result of waiting diligently on brahmins and recluses.[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Upasālha[/div][p]A wealthy brahmin of Rājagaha.  He lived near the monastery, but was an unbeliever and had nothing to do with the Buddha or his monks.  He had a wise and intelligent son.  When Upasālha was old, he told his son that, after death, he wished to be burnt in a cemetery unpolluted by any outcast.  Being asked by the son to point out such a spot, he took him to Gijjhakūta and showed him a place.  As they were descending the hill, the Buddha, perceiving their upanissaya, waited for them at the foot, and when they met he asked where they had been.  Having heard their story, he related the Upasālha Jātaka, showing that in the past, too, Upasālha had been fastidious about cemeteries.  At the conclusion of the discourse, both father and son were established in the First Fruit of the Path.  J.ii.54ff.[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Ulūka Jātaka (No.  270)[/div][p]Once the birds wanted to select a king because all the other animals had kings.  It was proposed to make the owl king, but when the vote came to be taken, a crow stood up and objected, saying: "If this is how he looks when he is being consecrated king, how will he look when he is angry?" The owl gave him chase and the birds chose a goose instead.  Here began the eternal enmity of the owl and the crow.  The story was told by the Buddha when it was reported to him that the owls near Jetavana were killing numerous crows nightly.  J.ii.351-4.[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Uppāda Sutta[/div][hr][p]1. Uppāda Sutta.-See Uppanna Sutta.[/p][p][/p][p]2. Uppāda Sutta.-The arising of the four elements is the uprising of suffering, their ceasing is its cessation.  S.ii.175.[/p][p][/p][p]3. Uppāda Sutta.-Same as No.  2, but with the substitution of the five khandhas for the four elements.  S.iii.31f.[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Udaya Jātaka (No.  458)[/div][p]The story of Udayabhadda and Udayabhaddā (q.v.).  [/p][p][/p][p]The story was related in reference to a back-sliding monk; the details are given in the Kusa Jātaka.  [/p][p][/p][p]The Udaya Jātaka also bears certain resemblances to the Ananusociya Jātaka.[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Upekhā Sutta[/div][hr][p]1. Upekhā Sutta.  Ananda says that Sāriputta's senses are clean and his face translucent.  How has he spent the day? Sāriputta answers that he has been in the fourth jhāna, wherein is neither pleasure nor pain but pure equanimity.  S.iii.237.[/p][p][/p][p]2. Upekhā Sutta.-The idea of equanimity, if cultivated, conduces to great gain.  S.v.131.[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Udañcani Jātaka (No.  106)[/div][p]The Bodhisatta and his son lived in a hermitage.  One evening when the Bodhisatta came back with fruits to the hermitage, he found that his son had neither brought in food and wood nor lit the fire.  When questioned by his father, he answered that during the latter's absence a woman had tempted him, and was waiting outside for him to go with her, if he could obtain his father's consent.  The Bodhisatta, seeing that his son was greatly enamoured of the woman, gave his consent, adding that if ever he wished to come back he would be welcome.  The young man went away with the woman, but after some time, realising that he had to slave to satisfy her needs, he ran away from her and returned to his father (J.i.416-7).[/p][p][/p][p]For the circumstances relating to the telling of the story, see the Culla-Nārada-Kassapa Jātaka.[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Ukkhā Sutta[/div][p]It would be better to cultivate thoughts of love (mettā) at morning, noon and eventide, than to give a morning gift of one hundred ukkhās and the same at noon and in the evening (S.ii.264).  [/p][p][/p][p]The Commentary explains ukkhā as being a large pot with a large mouth (mahā-mukha-ukkhalī); SA.ii.164.[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Uttarā[/div][hr][p][b]1. Uttarā[/b].-A therī.  She was born in Kapilavatthu in a Sākyan family.  She became a lady of the Bodhisatta's court and later renounced the world with Pajāpatī Gotamī.  When she was developing insight, the Buddha appeared before her to encourage her and she became an arahant.  Thig.v.15; ThigA.21f.[/p][hr][p][b]2. Uttarā.[/b]-She was the daughter of a clansman's family in Sāvatthi.  Having heard Patācarā preach, she entered the Order and became an arahant.[/p][p]The Therīgāthā contains seven verses uttered by her after becoming an arahant, the result of her determination not to leave the sitting posture till she had won emancipation.  Later she repeated these verses to Patācārā.  Thig.vv.175-81; ThigA.161-2.[/p][hr][p][b]3. Uttarā.[/b]-In the Theragāthā two verses (Thag.vv.1020-1) are attributed to Ananda, as having been spoken by him in admonition to an upāsikā named Uttarā, who was filled with the idea of her own beauty.  Some say, however, that these verses were spoken in admonition to those who lost their heads at the sight of Ambapāli.  ThagA.ii.129.[/p][hr][p][b]4. Uttarā Nandamātā.[/b]-Chief of the lay-women disciples who waited on the Buddha (Bu.xxvi.20).  In the Anguttara Nikāya (i.26), she is described as the best of women disciples in meditative power (jhāyīnam), but this may refer to another Uttarā.  She is again mentioned (A.iv.347; AA.ii.791) in a list of eminent lay-women disciples, who observed the fast (uposatha) of the eight precepts.[/p][p]According to the Anguttara Commentary (i.240ff), she was the daughter of Punnasīha (Punnaka) (q.v.), a servitor of Sumana-setthi of Rājagaha.  Later, when Punnasīha was made dhana-setthi because of the immense wealth he gained by virtue of a meal given to Sāriputta, he held an almsgiving for the Buddha and his monks for seven days.  On the seventh day, at the end of the Buddha's sermon of thanksgiving, Punnasīha, his wife and daughter, all became Sotāpanna.[/p][p]When Sumana-setthi asked for Uttarā's hand for his son, his request was refused because Sumana's family did not belong to the Buddha's faith.  Punna sent word to Sumana that Uttarā was the Buddha's disciple and daily offered flowers to the Buddha, costing a kahāpana.  Later, however, when Sumana promised that Uttarā should be given flowers worth two kahāpanas, Punna agreed and Uttarā was married.  After several unsuccessful attempts to obtain her husband's permission to keep the fast, as she had done in her parents' house, she got from her father fifteen thousand kahāpanas and with these she purchased the services of a prostitute named Sirimā, to look after her husband for a fortnight, and with his consent she entered on a fortnight's uposatha.  On the last day of the fast, while Uttarā was busy preparing alms for the Buddha, her husband, walking along with Sirimā, saw her working hard and smiled, thinking what a fool she was not to enjoy her wealth.  Uttarā, seeing him, smiled at the thought of his folly in not making proper use of his wealth.  Sirimā, thinking that husband and wife were smiling at each other, regardless of her presence, flew into a fury and, seizing a pot of boiling oil, threw it at Uttarā's head.  But Uttarā was at that time full of compassion for Sirimā, and the oil, therefore, did not hurt her at all.  Sirimā, realising her grievous folly, begged forgiveness of Uttarā, who took her to the Buddha and related the whole story, asking that he should forgive her.  The Buddha preached to Sirimā and she became a Sotāpanna.[/p][p]The Vimānavatthu Commentary (pp.631ff; Vv.11f) and the Dhammapada Commentary (iii.302ff; see also iii.104) give the above story with several variations in detail.  According to these versions, at the end of the Buddha's sermon to Sirimā, Uttarā became a Sakadāgāmī and her husband and father-in-law Sotāpannas.[/p][p]After death Uttarā was born in Tāvatimsa in a vimāna.  Moggallāna saw her in one of his visits to Tāvatimsa and, having learnt her story, repeated it to the Buddha.[/p][p]It is curious that Nanda is not mentioned in either account.  It has been suggested (E.g., Brethren 41, n.1) that Uttarā Nandamātā may be identical with Velukantakī-Nanda-mātā, but I do not think that the identification is justified.  Uttarā's story is given in the Visuddhi-Magga (p.313) to prove that fire cannot burn the body of a person who lives in love, and again (p.380-1; also Ps.ii.212; PsA.497), as an instance of psychic power being diffused by concentration.[/p][hr][p][b]5. Uttarā.[/b] Wife of Punnasīha (Punnaka) and mother of Uttarā (4).  (VvA.63; DhA.iii.302).[/p][p]For her story see Punnasīha.[/p][hr][p][b]6. Uttarā.[/b]-Daughter of Nandaka, general of Pingala, king of Surattha (PvA.241f).  For her story see Nandaka.[/p][hr][p][b]7. Uttarā.[/b]-A little yakkhinī, sister of Punabbasu.  For her story see Uttaramātā (2).[/p][hr][p][b]8. Uttarā.[/b]-Mother of Mangala Buddha.  Bu.iv.18; J.i.34.[/p][hr][p][b]9. Uttarā.[/b]-A brahmin lady, mother of Konāgamana Buddha, and also his Aggasāvikā.  J.i.43; D.ii.7; Bu.xxiv.17, 23.[/p][hr][p][b]10. Uttarā.[/b] Aggasāvikā of Nārada Buddha.  J.i.37; Bu.x.24.[/p][hr][p][b]11. Uttarā.[/b]-Wife of Paduma Buddha in his last lay life.  Bu.ix.18.[/p][hr][p][b]12. Uttarā.[/b]-One of the chief women supporters of Vipassī Buddha.  Bu.xx.30.[/p][hr][p][b]13. Uttarā.[/b]-Daughter of the banker Uttara.  She gave a meal of milk-rice to Mangala Buddha just before his Enlightenment (BuA.116).[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Ummadantī[/div][p]The daughter of the banker Tirītavaccha of Aritthapura.  When she came of age, she was so beautiful that all who saw her lost control of themselves.  At her father's request, Sivi, the king of the country (who was the Bodhisatta) sent fortune-tellers to examine her, with a view to making her his wife, but the brahmins, on seeing her, were so intoxicated with passion that Ummadantī had them driven out of the house.  They returned and told the king that she was a witch, and she was, therefore, given in marriage to Ahipāraka, son of the commander-in-chief.  Ummadantī bore the king a grudge for having refused her hand, and one feast day, when the king passed under her window, she threw flowers at him to attract his attention.  From the moment that the king saw Ummadantī, he was beside himself with longing for her and lay on his couch raving about her.  When Ahipāraka heard what had happened he offered his wife to the king, but Sivi was too righteous to hear of accepting the gift, and by a supreme effort of will he overcame his infatuation.[/p][p]In a former birth Ummadantī was born in a poor family of Benares, and on a certain festal day having seen some holy women clad in robes dyed scarlet with safflower she asked her parents for a similar robe.  Realising that they were too poor to afford the gift, she worked for a long time for another family, and they finally gave her a robe.  When she was about to don it, after a bath in the river, she saw a disciple of Kassapa Buddha standing without any proper clothes, his robes having been stolen from the river bank.  She first gave him half her garment, then, seeing how radiant he looked in it, she gave him also the other half and uttered a prayer that in a further existence she should surpass all other women in looks and be of maddening beauty.[/p][p]She is identified with the Therī Uppalavannā.  See also ThigA.192, v.28, quoted from the Apadāna.  [/p][p]The story is related in the Ummadantī Jātaka.  J.v.209ff.[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Udakarahada Sutta [/div][p]There are four kinds of sheets of water:[/p][p][/p][ul][li][p](1) Flat (uttāna) but deep in appearance (obhāsa); [/li][li][p](2) deep but flat in appearance; [/li][li][p](3) flat and flat in appearance; [/li][li][p](4) deep and deep in appearance.[/li][/ul][p]So, also, there are four classes of people: [/p][ul][li][p]handsome in appearance but shallow in mind; [/li][li][p]not handsome in appearance but deep in knowledge; [/li][li][p]neither handsome nor wise; [/li][li][p]both handsome and wise (A.ii.105-6).[/li][/ul]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Upasamā Therī[/div][p]She was born in a Sākyan family in Kapilavatthu and became a lady of the Bodhisatta's court.  Later, in the company of Pajāpatī Gotamī, she renounced the world and entered the Order.  One day, while she was meditating, the Buddha sent forth a ray of glory and admonished her.  She, thereupon, developed insight and became an arahant.  Thig.v.10; ThigA.12f.[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Uttaramātā[/div][hr][p]1. Uttaramātā.-Mother of Uttara, who was a son of Udena's minister.  (See Uttara 7.) She was miserly, and when her son gave alms she abused him, and spoke disparagingly of the holy men who accepted his gifts.  On one occasion, however, she approved of a gift of a tuft of peacock's feathers at the festival of dedication of a vihāra.  After death she was born as a peta.  Because of her approval of the gift of peacock's feathers she had lovely hair, but when she stepped into the river to drink water, all the water turned into blood.  (She had told her son that his gifts would turn into blood in his nest birth).  For fifty-five years she wandered, famished and thirsty, till one day, seeing the Elder Kankhā-Revata spending the day on the banks of the Ganges, she approached him, covering her nudity with her hair, and begged him for a drink.  The Elder, having learnt from her her story, gave food and drink and clothes to the monks on her behalf and she obtained release from her suffering and enjoyed great bliss (Pv.28f; PvA.140ff).[/p][p][/p][p]According to the Visuddhi-Magga (ii.382), Uttaramātā was able to go through the sky because of the psychic power inborn in her as a result of Kamma.  This probably refers to another woman.  (See below 2.)[/p][p][/p][hr][p]2. Uttaramātā.-A Yakkhinī, mother of Punabbasu and Uttarā.  Once as she passed Jetavana at sunset looking for food, with her daughter on her hip and holding her son by his finger, she saw the assembly, intently listening to the Buddha's sermon.  She, too, hoping to get some benefit, listened quietly and with great earnestness, hushing her children to quietness.  The Buddha preached in such a manner that both she and her son could understand, and at the end of the sermon they both became Sotāpannā.  She immediately got rid of her sad Yakkha-state and obtained heavenly bliss, and took up her residence in a tree near the Buddha's Fragrant Chamber.[/p][p]Little Uttarā was too young to realise the Truth.  S.i.210; SA.i.238-40; DA.ii.500f.[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Uvāla Thera[/div][p]He was examined by the Sangha in connection with an offence he had committed.  He first denied it, then confessed it, then denied it again, and made counter-charges and spoke lies, knowing them to be such.  The Buddha requested the monks to carry out the tassa-pāpiyyasikā-kamma against him (v.l.  Upavāla).  Vin.ii.85f; where the details of procedure are also given.[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Upassuti Sutta[/div][p]Once when the Buddha was staying in the Giñjakāvasatha in Nātikā, he meditated in solitude and uttered a teaching setting forth how, from the objects and the senses, arise consciousness and contact and, ultimately, the whole body of Ill.  A certain monk overheard this, and when the Buddha saw him, he asked the monk to learn the discourse by heart and bear it in mind, because it would lead to the righteous life.  S.iv.90f.[/p]</e>
  <e>[div class="huge"]Uppāde Sutta [/div][hr][p]1. Uppāde Sutta (2).-The eight conditions - right views, etc.  - come into being only on the arising of a Tathāgata.  S.v.14.[/p][p][/p][p]2. Uppāde Sutta.-The five controlling faculties (indriyāni) of saddhā, sati, etc., arise only upon the manifestation of a Tathāgata.  S.v.235.[/p]</e>
</xml>
